<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-06T15:44:27+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rebecca Platt</title><subtitle>Writing Stories and Code</subtitle><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><entry><title type="html">In The Deep End</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/29/InTheDeepEnd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In The Deep End" /><published>2024-08-29T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-08-29T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/08/29/InTheDeepEnd</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/08/29/InTheDeepEnd.html"><![CDATA[<span>Exposure to a wider range of technology processes and services can be great for your career. Earlier this year, I changed jobs to do just that - moving from working with a specialised area to a more widely used technology. Apart from broadening your range of skills, working in a new environment can also be great for your career in terms of building cross-industry knowledge, providing networking opportunities, and challenging yourself in new capacities.</span><br /></p>
<h3 class="header-anchor-post">Skill Diversification</h3>
No two teams work the same way, but there can be a lot of overlap in the processes. Taking part in a variety of teams, roles, and workplaces will almost inevitably expose you to a myriad of tools and methods. For example, since changing jobs, I've begun working extensively with CI tools like TeamCity and deployment automation tools like Octopus Deploy, as well as diving into API development. These new skills have not only broadened my technical expertise but also opened up opportunities for me to work on more complex and dynamic projects. Diversifying the number of skills you have and tools you have mastered will open up your opportunities to a wider range of options.</span><br /></p>
<h3 class="header-anchor-post">Unique Perspective with Cross-Industry Knowledge</h3>
Working in a range of different areas means that you can take your learnings from previous experiences and apply them to new contexts. The greater diversity of experience you have, the greater diversity of thought you will be able to bring to new projects, enabling some truly innovative and out-of-the-box solutions.</span><br /></p>
<h3 class="header-anchor-post">Networking Opportunities</h3>
This may be stating the obvious, but did you know different people work in other teams? Shocking, I know. Interacting with new teams and their stakeholders will help you broaden your professional network. Connecting with more peers, mentors, and industry leaders is another excellent way to gain exposure to new ideas and opportunities.</span><br /></p>
<h3 class="header-anchor-post">A New Challenge</h3>
Sometimes, we just get bored and need a change. Changing our work is one sure-fire way to mitigate any sensation of boredom, as it's much more difficult to be bored when figuring out a whole new way of working.  This shake-up can be great for our mental health, as increased variety can keep your work feeling engaging and stimulate continuous learning.</span><br /></p><p>Change can be intimidating, but it is essential for personal growth. Working in a new team or with a new technology enables you to diversify your skills, gain cross-industry knowledge, network with more people, and face new challenges - all of which can enhance your professional growth, satisfaction, and opportunities. If you’re feeling stuck, step out of your comfort zone and dive into the deep end. Embrace the new experiences and opportunities, and discover what is waiting for you out there.</p>
<br>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exposure to a wider range of technology processes and services can be great for your career. Earlier this year, I changed jobs to do just that - moving from working with a specialised area to a more widely used technology. Apart from broadening your range of skills, working in a new environment can also be great for your career in terms of building cross-industry knowledge, providing networking opportunities, and challenging yourself in new capacities. Skill Diversification No two teams work the same way, but there can be a lot of overlap in the processes. Taking part in a variety of teams, roles, and workplaces will almost inevitably expose you to a myriad of tools and methods. For example, since changing jobs, I've begun working extensively with CI tools like TeamCity and deployment automation tools like Octopus Deploy, as well as diving into API development. These new skills have not only broadened my technical expertise but also opened up opportunities for me to work on more complex and dynamic projects. Diversifying the number of skills you have and tools you have mastered will open up your opportunities to a wider range of options. Unique Perspective with Cross-Industry Knowledge Working in a range of different areas means that you can take your learnings from previous experiences and apply them to new contexts. The greater diversity of experience you have, the greater diversity of thought you will be able to bring to new projects, enabling some truly innovative and out-of-the-box solutions. Networking Opportunities This may be stating the obvious, but did you know different people work in other teams? Shocking, I know. Interacting with new teams and their stakeholders will help you broaden your professional network. Connecting with more peers, mentors, and industry leaders is another excellent way to gain exposure to new ideas and opportunities. A New Challenge Sometimes, we just get bored and need a change. Changing our work is one sure-fire way to mitigate any sensation of boredom, as it's much more difficult to be bored when figuring out a whole new way of working. This shake-up can be great for our mental health, as increased variety can keep your work feeling engaging and stimulate continuous learning.Change can be intimidating, but it is essential for personal growth. Working in a new team or with a new technology enables you to diversify your skills, gain cross-industry knowledge, network with more people, and face new challenges - all of which can enhance your professional growth, satisfaction, and opportunities. If you’re feeling stuck, step out of your comfort zone and dive into the deep end. Embrace the new experiences and opportunities, and discover what is waiting for you out there.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pride in June</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/25/PrideInJune.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pride in June" /><published>2024-06-25T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-06-25T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/06/25/PrideInJune</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/06/25/PrideInJune.html"><![CDATA[<p><span>It’s pride month! The time of year dedicated to celebrating the successes and raising awareness for the challenges still faced by the LGBTQ+ community. With the rise of anti-LGBTQ+ legislation sweeping the US in recent years and the seeming </span><a href="https://apnews.com/article/pride-target-lgbtq-0d0ade0c3ba9766884a9ed7ad92f31fe" target="_blank">lack of brands showing solidarity</a><span> this time around, it seemed an appropriate time to look back on the history and significance of the event.</span></p><p>While LGBTQ+ people have been around for as long as people have in general, this particular month of celebration has its roots in the 1960s. If you, like myself, were not around for this decade - consider the following:</p>
<ul>
    <li>
        <p><span>Homosexuality was considered a mental disorder in the </span><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diagnostic_and_Statistical_Manual_of_Mental_Disorders" target="_blank">Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</a></em><span> (and was not completely removed until 1987).</span></p></li>
    <li>
        <p><span>People were also losing their jobs. For example in 1953 American </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States" target="_blank">President</a><span> </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwight_D._Eisenhower" target="_blank">Dwight D. Eisenhower</a><span> issued </span><strong>Executive Order 10450,</strong><span> in which federal agencies were charged with reviewing their employees for anyone considered a security risk - which included anyone deemed to have a ‘sexual perversion’. They were seen as more susceptible to blackmail and were fired accordingly.</span></p>
    </li>
</ul>
<p>
There had been numerous movements, organisations, and protests prior, but it was the Stonewall Inn raid that sparked the gay liberation movement in the Western world. Taking place over multiple nights starting on June 28, 1969, police raided the Stonewall Inn in Manhattan. There, officers attempted to arrest any patrons dressed in a way that did not conform to the conventions of their perceived gender.</p><p>This was not an irregular event for gay bars in the city at the time. What was different this time, however, was that as the raid progressed a crowd began to form (consisting of patrons that had been released as well as passers-by). As they watched fights break out between police and those they had arrested, the crowd also grew violent as they transformed into a mob in their attempt to stop the injustice.</p>
<p>
There are plenty of articles and books that will do greater justice to explaining the events and impact of these riots than I am currently capable of doing. David Carter, author of Stonewall: The Riots that Sparked the Gay Revolution, wrote:</p><blockquote><p><em>‘Compared to these earlier events, Stonewall was of a different order for four reasons: it was the only sustained uprising, lasting six days; it was the only one that involved thousands of people; it was the only one that got much media coverage; and it was unique in engendering a new kind of militant organization (first the Gay Liberation Front and later the Gay Activists Alliance) as well as a new political ideology known as ”gay liberation.”’ - </em><a href="https://glreview.org/article/article-509/" target="_blank">What Made Stonewall Different</a></p></blockquote>
<p>
One year later, on the first anniversary of the Stonewall riots, the first Gay Pride marches in US history took place.</p><p>Over time, it extended from a day to a month-long event thanks to the collective efforts of various parts of the LGBTQ+ community. As far as I can tell, there was no particular single originator of the idea to extend the day to a month. Regardless, making the event longer enables a variety of events to take place. From parades to educational sessions, art exhibits, etc, a greater spotlight can shine on the progress made so far, sparking a wider conversation about the issues ongoing.</p>
<p>
<span>Unfortunately, while much has progressed since the original riots, there are still many inequalities that need addressing. With events organised globally (and available as virtual as well as in person), I recommend finding out about the Pride events happening near you, and how you can take part. Just remember, recognition and celebration of rights should not only be contained to a single month. There are still plenty of ways to </span><a href="https://hbr.org/2023/04/research-how-to-be-a-better-ally-to-the-lgbtq-community" target="_blank">support the community</a><span> and fight for equality, regardless of the time of year.</span></p>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s pride month! The time of year dedicated to celebrating the successes and raising awareness for the challenges still faced by the LGBTQ+ community. With the rise of anti-LGBTQ+ legislation sweeping the US in recent years and the seeming lack of brands showing solidarity this time around, it seemed an appropriate time to look back on the history and significance of the event.While LGBTQ+ people have been around for as long as people have in general, this particular month of celebration has its roots in the 1960s. If you, like myself, were not around for this decade - consider the following: Homosexuality was considered a mental disorder in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (and was not completely removed until 1987). People were also losing their jobs. For example in 1953 American President Dwight D. Eisenhower issued Executive Order 10450, in which federal agencies were charged with reviewing their employees for anyone considered a security risk - which included anyone deemed to have a ‘sexual perversion’. They were seen as more susceptible to blackmail and were fired accordingly. There had been numerous movements, organisations, and protests prior, but it was the Stonewall Inn raid that sparked the gay liberation movement in the Western world. Taking place over multiple nights starting on June 28, 1969, police raided the Stonewall Inn in Manhattan. There, officers attempted to arrest any patrons dressed in a way that did not conform to the conventions of their perceived gender.This was not an irregular event for gay bars in the city at the time. What was different this time, however, was that as the raid progressed a crowd began to form (consisting of patrons that had been released as well as passers-by). As they watched fights break out between police and those they had arrested, the crowd also grew violent as they transformed into a mob in their attempt to stop the injustice. There are plenty of articles and books that will do greater justice to explaining the events and impact of these riots than I am currently capable of doing. David Carter, author of Stonewall: The Riots that Sparked the Gay Revolution, wrote:‘Compared to these earlier events, Stonewall was of a different order for four reasons: it was the only sustained uprising, lasting six days; it was the only one that involved thousands of people; it was the only one that got much media coverage; and it was unique in engendering a new kind of militant organization (first the Gay Liberation Front and later the Gay Activists Alliance) as well as a new political ideology known as ”gay liberation.”’ - What Made Stonewall Different One year later, on the first anniversary of the Stonewall riots, the first Gay Pride marches in US history took place.Over time, it extended from a day to a month-long event thanks to the collective efforts of various parts of the LGBTQ+ community. As far as I can tell, there was no particular single originator of the idea to extend the day to a month. Regardless, making the event longer enables a variety of events to take place. From parades to educational sessions, art exhibits, etc, a greater spotlight can shine on the progress made so far, sparking a wider conversation about the issues ongoing. Unfortunately, while much has progressed since the original riots, there are still many inequalities that need addressing. With events organised globally (and available as virtual as well as in person), I recommend finding out about the Pride events happening near you, and how you can take part. Just remember, recognition and celebration of rights should not only be contained to a single month. There are still plenty of ways to support the community and fight for equality, regardless of the time of year.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Just Five More Minutes: Applying Social Media Consumption Tactics To Books</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/30/SocialMediaTacticsBooks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Just Five More Minutes: Applying Social Media Consumption Tactics To Books" /><published>2024-04-30T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-04-30T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/04/30/SocialMediaTacticsBooks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/04/30/SocialMediaTacticsBooks.html"><![CDATA[I don’t like social media. Sure it has its uses, in enabling me to keep in contact with family and friends across the world, and sure it’s occasionally filled with photos of kittens and puppies and whatnot, but I still don’t like it. I don’t like the fact that I can doom-scroll for hours, or that I do so on far too regular a basis. I don’t think anyone does, and so this presumably isn’t shocking news.
<p/>
What I do like though, is reading. Not memes and status updates, but stories. Yet no matter how much I enjoy it, I never seem to find the time to read, but I always have too much time for social media.
<p/>
I know that social media companies have put a lot of effort and research into making their apps as addictive as possible, to hold user engagement. I also know that I am susceptible to the tactics they have used, as evidenced by my sheer amount of social media usage.
<p/>
So why not try apply the same tactics that have worked so well on me, to reading? Can I make reading books as addictive as social media?
<p/>
There are a few methods that companies use that I focused on to emulate for my experiment. They are; endless scrolling, push notifications, and social comparison.

<p/>

<h2 class="section-heading">Endless Scrolling</h2>
<br/>
<img src="http://blogs.studentlife.utoronto.ca/lifeatuoft/files/2015/11/thisissomuchfun.gif" alt="Image of hand scrolling the text 'This is so much fun' on a phone" width="60%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">
<p/>
As the name suggests, endless scrolling is an interaction design pattern, where content loads as the person scrolls without interruption. Most ebook apps use pagination, where the person flips the pages just like they would with a physical book. Flipping to the next page uses more effort than scrolling down slightly, and it also gives you a natural point in the process to decide to stop reading and do something else. By switching to an infinite scroll model, it requires much less energy to view the next part of content, and as there’s no ‘checkpoint’ where you stop momentarily, you are much more likely to continue passively consuming the content.
<p/>
To enable this for my reading, I switched from the app I was using to use Kindle, which has inbuilt settings to allow for the endless scroll.

<p/>

<h2 class="section-heading">Push Notifications</h2>
<br/>
<img src="https://cdn.dribbble.com/users/409677/screenshots/3947273/noti-ps.gif" alt="A phone with a notification speech bubble floating above it" width="60%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">
<br/>

Spend any time near a modern phone, and you’ll know everything you need about push notifications. Multiple studies have demonstrated the effectiveness of push notifications in regards to user engagement and retention. According to the <a href="https://www.humanetech.com/brain-science" target="_blank">Center for Humane Technology</a>, “Notifications (vibrations, red dots, flashing lights, banners) constantly trigger the salience network, effectively fooling us that something new but trivial is urgent.” If you want to make notifications even more effective, they should also include an element of novelty. Novelty in activity results in several impacts on the brain, and the most valuable impact in this context is that it can induce a release of dopamine, aka the “feel-good” hormone.
<p/>
To replicate this for reading, I used a reminder app (<a href="https://keep.google.com/" target="_blank">Google Keep</a>) to send me a variety of different notifications at varying times.
<p/>
<img src="/img/posts/BookNotifications.jpg" alt="Screenshot of notifications, including 'The world can wait, but your book can't', 'Pause, breathe, and read', 'It's reading o'clock', 'Time to book some reading time!', 
Bookmark now for reading!', 'A book a day keeps reality away', 'Time to read!', and 'Reading? How novel'" style="width:60%;display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">

<p/>

<h2 class="section-heading">Social Comparison</h2>
<br/>
<img src="https://cdn.dribbble.com/users/1129235/screenshots/3362278/gif5.gif" alt="Three people stood on rising and lowering platforms. The person in the centre is sad when their platform is lower than the others." width="60%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">
<br/>

Humans are social animals. We thrive because of connection and cooperation. We also thrive by comparison, as we evaluate our traits and abilities by contrasting ourselves with our peers. Social media allows us to overload on a distorted and over-sanitized version of this, as we can use it to compare ourselves with the very best achievements of every person we have ever met (resulting in <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10309264/" target="_blank">impacted levels of self-esteem</a>, to the surprise of no one).
<p/>
To apply social comparison to reading, all you need is to sign up to a website such as Goodreads or StoryGraph. In both sites, users can record which books they have read before, are reading currently, what they thought of them, what they want to read next, and how many books they have read this year so far. More importantly, you can then connect with others and see what they read, what they rate, and compare just how much more they have read than you so far this year.

<p/>

<h2 class="section-heading">The Results</h2>
<p/>
Before I started this experiment, I was about halfway through reading Great Expectations by Charles Dickens, and it had taken me 12 weeks to reach that point. After I implemented the changes described above, I finished reading the second half of the book in 10 days. I would marvel at how much of an impact it made, but right now I’d rather get back to reading.
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I don’t like social media. Sure it has its uses, in enabling me to keep in contact with family and friends across the world, and sure it’s occasionally filled with photos of kittens and puppies and whatnot, but I still don’t like it. I don’t like the fact that I can doom-scroll for hours, or that I do so on far too regular a basis. I don’t think anyone does, and so this presumably isn’t shocking news. What I do like though, is reading. Not memes and status updates, but stories. Yet no matter how much I enjoy it, I never seem to find the time to read, but I always have too much time for social media. I know that social media companies have put a lot of effort and research into making their apps as addictive as possible, to hold user engagement. I also know that I am susceptible to the tactics they have used, as evidenced by my sheer amount of social media usage. So why not try apply the same tactics that have worked so well on me, to reading? Can I make reading books as addictive as social media? There are a few methods that companies use that I focused on to emulate for my experiment. They are; endless scrolling, push notifications, and social comparison.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Get To The Point</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/12/GetToThePoint.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Get To The Point" /><published>2024-03-12T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-03-12T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/03/12/GetToThePoint</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/03/12/GetToThePoint.html"><![CDATA[How many words do you need?
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How many words do you need?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review: Your Head Is A Houseboat by Campbell Walker</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/12/Book-Head-Houseboat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review: Your Head Is A Houseboat by Campbell Walker" /><published>2024-01-12T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-01-12T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/01/12/Book-Head-Houseboat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/12/Book-Head-Houseboat.html"><![CDATA[It’s that time of year again, when people start taking stock of the year that was and think ahead wondering how they can improve their lives. Countless New Year's resolutions are being planned at this very moment. For a fair few people, their resolutions will involve focusing on improving their mental health. It’s a worthy goal no matter what your mental landscape is like. With that in mind, ‘Your Head Is A Houseboat: A Chaotic Guide to Mental Clarity’ by Campbell Walker is a great book, one that anyone on a (mental) self-improvement journey should read.
<p/>
<img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/81yJxESnSFL._SL1500_.jpg" alt="Book Cover for Your Head is a Houseboat: A Chaotic Guide to Mental Clarity By Campbell Walker" width="60%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">About The Author</h2>
Campbell Walker, also known as Struthless, is a content creator on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@struthless" target="_blank">YouTube</a> (and various other platforms) that I’ve been following for a few years now.
<p/>
He makes great videos about so many interesting topics, with the overall theme of the videos covering self-reflective journaling, art, and introspection. In general (and based entirely on the content he produces), he seems like a decent guy who’s just trying to make everyone’s head a nicer place to live in.
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">What The Book Is About</h2>
Achieving mental clarity by taking complex concepts and the latest advances in psychology, and making them more accessible to the average person through a fully illustrated houseboat tour metaphor. To the surprise of absolutely no one familiar with Cam’s content, the book is filled with anthropomorphic metacognitions in the form of mean bosses and sock puppets and animals, as well as journaling exercises at the end of each chapter to ensure that the reader fully understands the concepts presented before moving on to the next section.
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">My Thoughts</h2>
I have to hand it to him, ‘mental clarity’ was a great description of exactly what this book provides. Several times when I was following along with the activities at the end of the chapters I’d have an epiphany, followed by moments of genuine relief from the constant never ending thought process that is my brain. I actually felt moments of clarity. While I enjoy his videos, I truly did not expect to be as impacted by the book as I was. The concepts covered in the book were not new to me, but the way in which they were covered brought everything into a new light. The analogies resonated with me, and the full-colour illustrations were such a lovely bonus too. I think that this would be a great book to read regardless of whether it’s your first or fifty-first time reading about mental health and self-development.
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s that time of year again, when people start taking stock of the year that was and think ahead wondering how they can improve their lives. Countless New Year's resolutions are being planned at this very moment. For a fair few people, their resolutions will involve focusing on improving their mental health. It’s a worthy goal no matter what your mental landscape is like. With that in mind, ‘Your Head Is A Houseboat: A Chaotic Guide to Mental Clarity’ by Campbell Walker is a great book, one that anyone on a (mental) self-improvement journey should read. About The Author Campbell Walker, also known as Struthless, is a content creator on YouTube (and various other platforms) that I’ve been following for a few years now. He makes great videos about so many interesting topics, with the overall theme of the videos covering self-reflective journaling, art, and introspection. In general (and based entirely on the content he produces), he seems like a decent guy who’s just trying to make everyone’s head a nicer place to live in. What The Book Is About Achieving mental clarity by taking complex concepts and the latest advances in psychology, and making them more accessible to the average person through a fully illustrated houseboat tour metaphor. To the surprise of absolutely no one familiar with Cam’s content, the book is filled with anthropomorphic metacognitions in the form of mean bosses and sock puppets and animals, as well as journaling exercises at the end of each chapter to ensure that the reader fully understands the concepts presented before moving on to the next section. My Thoughts I have to hand it to him, ‘mental clarity’ was a great description of exactly what this book provides. Several times when I was following along with the activities at the end of the chapters I’d have an epiphany, followed by moments of genuine relief from the constant never ending thought process that is my brain. I actually felt moments of clarity. While I enjoy his videos, I truly did not expect to be as impacted by the book as I was. The concepts covered in the book were not new to me, but the way in which they were covered brought everything into a new light. The analogies resonated with me, and the full-colour illustrations were such a lovely bonus too. I think that this would be a great book to read regardless of whether it’s your first or fifty-first time reading about mental health and self-development.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Waiting For A Train: A Guide To Understanding Sunk-cost Fallacy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/29/SunkCostFallacy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waiting For A Train: A Guide To Understanding Sunk-cost Fallacy" /><published>2023-11-29T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-11-29T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/11/29/SunkCostFallacy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/29/SunkCostFallacy.html"><![CDATA[As I write this, I'm currently about 40 minutes into waiting for a train at the station. The overhead voice pops up every now and again, to say that trains have been delayed and that they're "sorry for any inconvenience." It makes you wonder how long they will say that a train is delayed, and when they'll just say it's cancelled instead. It's also giving me plenty of time to think about the phenomenon called "sunk-cost fallacy".
<h2 class="section-heading">Definition and Explanation</h2>
<br/>
<blockquote class="blockquote"><b>Sunk-cost fallacy</b>: the phenomenon whereby a person is reluctant to abandon a strategy or course of action because they have invested heavily in it, even when it is clear that abandonment would be more beneficial.
"the sunk-cost fallacy creeps into a lot of major financial decisions"</blockquote>
<figcaption>— <a href="https://languages.oup.com/google-dictionary-en/" target="_blank">Oxford Languages</a></figcaption>
<p/>
As a real world example: the longer I'm stood here, the less likely I am to leave because I've invested so much time in waiting for this train. I 'just know' that a train will appear the moment after I leave. So I'm waiting.
Based on how many people are around me, this would seem to be a common response to events.

<h2 class="section-heading">Cognitive Biases</h2>
<br/>
The reason it is considered a ‘fallacy’ is because it involves decision making in an irrational manner. I can’t get back the time I’ve used waiting at the station already, no matter what I do - so from an economic view-point, there’s no point including it as a factor in future decision making.
<p/>
This type on thinking can be considered as a form of loss aversion - which is a form of cognitive bias that in behavioural economic terms means the pain of loss is felt more severely than an equivalent gain. (For example, losing $10 would feel worse then finding $10.)
<p/>
The fun part of all this though is that even when you’re aware of the irrationality of it all, most people will still continue to wait for the train.

<h2 class="section-heading">Recognizing Sunk-Cost Fallacy</h2>
<br/>
Of course, it’s not always time that can be lost due to this fallacy - these costs can be financial, emotional, reputational, and so on. Knowing how to spot them can be difficult. Keep an eye out for:
<ul>
    <li>rationalizing or justifying your choice to continue</li>
    <li>emotions such as guilt, fear, or pride that may be influencing your judgment or preventing you from considering alternatives</li>
</ul>

<h2 class="section-heading">Consequences of Sunk-Cost Fallacy</h2>
<br/>
Depending on the situation, the consequences can range from ‘trivial’ to  ‘catastrophic’. Forty minutes of time wasted can be either, depending on your circumstances. Other forms of sunk-costs such as financial or emotional stress however, may have a greater negative impact.
<p/>
It’s not just individuals that succumb to sunk cost fallacy on occasion, it can happen at the corporate level too. This was most famously shown during the Concorde project, where the British and French governments did not realise that by taking the cost of the project so far into account and including it in their rationale to continue, they were perpetuating loss aversion. This ended up costing them £1.5–2.1 billion in 1976, which would equal an estimated £10.5–15.7 billion in 2022.

<h2 class="section-heading">Overcoming Sunk-Cost Fallacy</h2>
<br/>
So how do you decide whether it’s best to keep waiting for the train, or whether it’s time to leave?
<p/>
One way is to consider the opportunity cost for the end goal, and how achievable it is now. For example a 40 minute delay would be annoying if you were heading into work for the day, but catastrophic if you were trying to meet up with someone on their 30 minute lunch break.
<p/>
Another way is to develop exit strategies. In this case, before heading out to the train station consider in advance how long you’re willing to wait at the station in general. Planning in advance how and when to cut losses can make it easier to do so when the situation arises.
<p/>
However you decide to make your decision, you can do so comfortable in the knowledge that by overcoming sunk-cost fallacy, you are enabling yourself to make better, more resilient, and more adaptable and rational decisions.
<p/>
If you’re stuck waiting for your own train (literally or metaphorically) and have any suggestions for alternative ways to combat this fallacy, share them in the comments below.]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As I write this, I'm currently about 40 minutes into waiting for a train at the station. The overhead voice pops up every now and again, to say that trains have been delayed and that they're "sorry for any inconvenience." It makes you wonder how long they will say that a train is delayed, and when they'll just say it's cancelled instead. It's also giving me plenty of time to think about the phenomenon called "sunk-cost fallacy". Definition and Explanation Sunk-cost fallacy: the phenomenon whereby a person is reluctant to abandon a strategy or course of action because they have invested heavily in it, even when it is clear that abandonment would be more beneficial. "the sunk-cost fallacy creeps into a lot of major financial decisions" — Oxford Languages As a real world example: the longer I'm stood here, the less likely I am to leave because I've invested so much time in waiting for this train. I 'just know' that a train will appear the moment after I leave. So I'm waiting. Based on how many people are around me, this would seem to be a common response to events.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Develop, Debug, and Deploy at DDD Perth 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/10/13/DDDPerth2023.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Develop, Debug, and Deploy at DDD Perth 2023" /><published>2023-10-13T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-10-13T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/10/13/DDDPerth2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/10/13/DDDPerth2023.html"><![CDATA[DDD Perth is an annual event that is held in October, that is open to everyone in the software industry. Its goal is to be an inclusive non-profit conference for the Perth software community. One way that it attempts to achieve this is by having a democratically chosen agenda with blind voting. With 1400 attendees, 5 tracks of talks, 30 speakers, 20 sponsors and 50+ volunteers, it needed a lot of space. It’s no surprise that it took place at Optus Stadium. Below are some of the highlights from the day.

<h2 class="section-heading">What Does DDD Stand For?</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">“DDD Perth started out its life as part of the Developer! Developer! Developer! series of events and while our heritage is as a developer-focussed conference, DDD Perth is not just for developers, but for all professionals in the software industry. These days we don't expand DDD - it's not an acronym for us anymore, but if people insist then we might say Designer, Developer and Data Scientist, or is it DevOps, Data architect, distributed tester?”</blockquote><figcaption>- <a href="https://dddperth.com/about"target="_blank">About DDD Perth</a></figcaption>

<h2 class="section-heading">Speaker Highlights</h2>
The sessions I went to were fantastic overall, but it's incredible that I only got to hear approximately 25% of the talks because, aside from the keynotes, there were five tracks of presentations going on at once. If I had to pick one favourite it would be “The Visible Developer: Why You Shouldn't Blend In” by Heather Downing. It was a great way to kick off the day as the talk at its core was about getting out of your comfort zone, and in particular to “run towards the thing that scares you”. The talk was focused on professional networking and self-advocacy, but I can see it applying to many areas of life.
<p/>
<img src="/img/posts/Heather.jpg" alt="Photo of a woman stood on stage presenting" style="width:100%">
<p/>
If I had the power to force people to watch one other talk, it would be “Nerds on a Plane: What We Can Learn from the Aviation Industry” by Sarah Young. The aviation industry has done a lot of work to create a blameless culture to enable people to speak up when they notice an issue. With their amazing safety record speaking for themselves, this talk covered the concept of applying those same principles to software development and cyber security.
<p/>
Finally, I’d also like to highlight the talk “Less Boring Tests - An Introduction to Property-Based Testing” by Wes Toleman. I was lucky enough to view and give feedback on this talk before DDD, and Wes did an excellent job of advocating for property-based testing.
<p/>
<img src="/img/posts/Wes.jpg" alt="Photo of a man stood on stage presenting" style="width:100%">
<p/>
(Links to these talks will be added when they are made available online.)

<h2 class="section-heading">Hallway Track</h2>
Sometimes known as the most important track, the hallway track is the area with refreshments and booths from the sponsors that allow attendees to find out more about both the sponsors and others around them. Quite a few booths were running, and based on my swag haul it looks like socks were the most popular merch item this year. The keyring glasses cleaner cloth was a genius idea by Keystart; it’s great to see the booths branching out into more creative merchandise.
<p/>
Even though getting merchandise is great, the main benefit of the hallway track is networking. It’s great to catch up with so many people that I haven't seen in ages, and I got to meet lots of new people as well through mutual connections. Like Heather said in her keynote, having a large and valuable network is fantastic for advancing your career, and everyone was very open and welcoming.
<p/>
Networking may have been the highlight, but winning a statue of OctoCat from GitHub was a very close second.
<p/>
<img src="/img/posts/Octocat.jpg" alt="Photo of Octocat statue" style="width:100%">
<p/>
<p/>
<hr>
<br/>
<h4>While You're Here...</h4>
I have been nominated for a Women in Technology WA Inc. (WiTWA) award!
<br/>
Voting is open for a few more days, so please vote <a href="https://witwaawards.awardstage.com/public/judging/carousel?EntryId=129144"target="_blank">here</a>.
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[DDD Perth is an annual event that is held in October, that is open to everyone in the software industry. Its goal is to be an inclusive non-profit conference for the Perth software community. One way that it attempts to achieve this is by having a democratically chosen agenda with blind voting. With 1400 attendees, 5 tracks of talks, 30 speakers, 20 sponsors and 50+ volunteers, it needed a lot of space. It’s no surprise that it took place at Optus Stadium. Below are some of the highlights from the day.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Technology Trends at YOW!Perth 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/09/19/YOWPerth2023.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Technology Trends at YOW!Perth 2023" /><published>2023-09-19T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-09-19T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/09/19/YOWPerth2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/09/19/YOWPerth2023.html"><![CDATA[YOW!Perth, an annual conference held in September, brings together technology professionals for two days of knowledge-sharing and networking. It’s a great opportunity to hear from industry experts and leaders and to dive into the latest technology trends. I attended both days and have included some highlights below.
<h2 class="section-heading">About YOW</h2>
YOW!Perth is a tech conference that <i>“brings together internationally recognised experts and developers to encourage excellence and innovation in the APAC centered technology community.”</i> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/yow-conference/?originalSubdomain=au" target="_blank">YOW! Conferences</a>
<p/>
Fun fact: ‘YOW’ is not an acronym. Originally the conference was called ‘JAOO’ which stood for Java and Object Oriented languages, but after hearing various attempts at saying that with an Australian accent, they decided to change it to 'YOW'.
<h2 class="section-heading">Key Topics</h2>
Conferences in general are a great way to find out what the latest trends are in the industry. I found that this year the trends across the talks were focused on ‘soft skills’ and concepts rather than any particular technology, which was refreshing. The topics that stood out for me were:
<ul>
    <li>the importance of simplicity in architectural design to avoid common pitfalls (like over-engineering/over-complicating solutions),</li>
    <li>managing cognitive load and context switching,</li>
    <li>and awareness of and managing bias.</li>
</ul>
<p/>
Of course, there was one AI talk, which was a pretty fun bedtime story generator. It was a great example used to discuss common ‘things to keep in mind’ regarding AI.
<h2 class="section-heading">Notable Speakers</h2>
If I could only choose one of the presentations to recommend, it would be “Cultivating Instinct” by Katrina Owen. Katrina’s talk was about the difference between experts and novices (with a focus on development, but the concepts can relate regardless of field), and how perceptual learning and other training methods of growing intuition can be used to bridge that gap.
<p/>
Another talk that I enjoyed was “Is Software Engineering Real Engineering?” by Hillel Wayne. Hillel’s talk was an examination of what engineering is, by comparing software engineering with a variety of other engineering disciplines. By doing so he can contrast, compare, and ultimately explore what engineering truly is and what lessons can be learned in the process.
<p/>
(When the videos are released online, I’ll update here with the links.)
<h2 class="section-heading">Networking Opportunities</h2>
As always there was the ‘hallway track’. Sometimes known as the most important track, it was the area with refreshments and booths from the sponsors that allowed attendees to find out more about both the sponsors and others around them. Meeting up with old friends and making new connections, I do have to give a shout-out to the organisers for creating such a friendly and welcoming environment for everyone. In particular, I like their use of the ‘Pac-Man’ rule: “When standing as a group of people, always leave room for 1 person to join your group.” This rule made it much easier to join in with existing conversations, so I hope future conferences will continue to use it.
<p/>
<blockquote class="blockquote">“The future is already here - it's just not evenly distributed”</blockquote>
<figcaption>— William Gibson</figcaption>
<p/>
YOW!Perth 2023 was a testament to the ever-evolving world of technology. The concepts covered felt apt, and as always I have far too many ideas for projects inspired by the presentations. Conferences are a great way to hear new perspectives and YOW!Perth delivered on that front. Here’s hoping I can attend again next year!
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[YOW!Perth, an annual conference held in September, brings together technology professionals for two days of knowledge-sharing and networking. It’s a great opportunity to hear from industry experts and leaders and to dive into the latest technology trends. I attended both days and have included some highlights below. About YOW YOW!Perth is a tech conference that “brings together internationally recognised experts and developers to encourage excellence and innovation in the APAC centered technology community.” - YOW! Conferences Fun fact: ‘YOW’ is not an acronym. Originally the conference was called ‘JAOO’ which stood for Java and Object Oriented languages, but after hearing various attempts at saying that with an Australian accent, they decided to change it to 'YOW'. Key Topics Conferences in general are a great way to find out what the latest trends are in the industry. I found that this year the trends across the talks were focused on ‘soft skills’ and concepts rather than any particular technology, which was refreshing. The topics that stood out for me were: the importance of simplicity in architectural design to avoid common pitfalls (like over-engineering/over-complicating solutions), managing cognitive load and context switching, and awareness of and managing bias. Of course, there was one AI talk, which was a pretty fun bedtime story generator. It was a great example used to discuss common ‘things to keep in mind’ regarding AI. Notable Speakers If I could only choose one of the presentations to recommend, it would be “Cultivating Instinct” by Katrina Owen. Katrina’s talk was about the difference between experts and novices (with a focus on development, but the concepts can relate regardless of field), and how perceptual learning and other training methods of growing intuition can be used to bridge that gap. Another talk that I enjoyed was “Is Software Engineering Real Engineering?” by Hillel Wayne. Hillel’s talk was an examination of what engineering is, by comparing software engineering with a variety of other engineering disciplines. By doing so he can contrast, compare, and ultimately explore what engineering truly is and what lessons can be learned in the process. (When the videos are released online, I’ll update here with the links.) Networking Opportunities As always there was the ‘hallway track’. Sometimes known as the most important track, it was the area with refreshments and booths from the sponsors that allowed attendees to find out more about both the sponsors and others around them. Meeting up with old friends and making new connections, I do have to give a shout-out to the organisers for creating such a friendly and welcoming environment for everyone. In particular, I like their use of the ‘Pac-Man’ rule: “When standing as a group of people, always leave room for 1 person to join your group.” This rule made it much easier to join in with existing conversations, so I hope future conferences will continue to use it. “The future is already here - it's just not evenly distributed” — William Gibson YOW!Perth 2023 was a testament to the ever-evolving world of technology. The concepts covered felt apt, and as always I have far too many ideas for projects inspired by the presentations. Conferences are a great way to hear new perspectives and YOW!Perth delivered on that front. Here’s hoping I can attend again next year!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Rules Are Not The Goal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/08/31/RulesAreNotTheGoal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rules Are Not The Goal" /><published>2023-08-31T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-08-31T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/08/31/RulesAreNotTheGoal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/08/31/RulesAreNotTheGoal.html"><![CDATA[I made it a goal for myself when I first started this blog to post at least once a month. This condition was imposed with good intentions, to ensure that I would write consistently. This was to improve my writing, which was the main goal for starting the blog in the first place. But while it was well-intentioned, I don't believe it was the right move. 
It has been detrimental in two ways: first, it has increased unnecessary stress, and second, it has slowed down my writing pace.
<p/>
The obligation to post 'every month' is what causes the stress. By setting a time requirement, I have inadvertently set myself a deadline to post by the end of every month. Posting a day later (on the 1st) would still count as a failure in reaching my goal. This arbitrary deadline has made the approach of the end of the month something I dread, and to avoid feeling like I've failed in my goal I'll write something/anything to avoid that. This means the topics are chosen based on how quick and easy they would be to rush out, rather than what I am most interested in at the time.
<p/>
The second way that it impacted me is that whenever I thought of another topic I would like to write about, instead of starting on it right away I would only add them to my backlog. This provided me with a wide range of options at the end of the month (even if I would only select the 'easy' ones). As a result, I didn't write anything until the end of the month, which made me less consistent in my writing than I would have been.
<p/>
So what's the plan? The monthly restriction was in place for positive reasons, and despite slowing down my writing and raising my stress levels, it has also made sure that I update frequently.
<p/>
At this point the negatives outweigh the positives, so it's time to change. For more effective goal setting, a few things need to change. Let's start by using the SMART goal framework. This can be used to check that the goal is Specific, Measurable, Achievable, Relevant, and Time-Bound.
<p/>
<b>Specific</b>: For a goal to be specific, it needs to be able to answer questions such as "Who is responsible?" and "What needs to happen?". In this case, 'writing' needs to happen, by me specifically.
<p/>
<b>Measurable</b>: When a goal is quantifiable, we can measure the progress and also know that the goal has been achieved. Last time we tried measuring the number of posts completed in a month and it didn't work, so let's do a different time-based this time. Instead of measuring the number of posts, we will track the amount of time spent writing.
<p/>
<b>Achievable</b>: As tempting as it would be to declare that I should write every waking hour, that's not realistic. Considering the other obligations I have in my day-to-day life, an achievable amount of time I can set aside is 30 minutes minimum, ideally every day but in actuality at least 4 days a week. Of course, this may change if I need to, determining what is realistic may take some trial and error.
<p/>
<b>Relevant</b>: This is where we ask "Why?". If the overarching goal is to improve writing, then setting a goal to go horse riding won't help. But making it writing-related will - and for my scenario it doesn't have to be blog-specific writing, as my writing goals are wider than that. 
<p/>
<b>Time-Bound</b>: This relates to making the goal measurable. All goals must end eventually, and having a time when even 'repeating' tasks are done means that they are much more likely to be completed. The time frame for this goal is the next three months, chosen thanks to this article: <a href="https://www.vox.com/even-better/23835758/divide-life-semesters-not-in-school-motivation-goals" target="_blank">Why you should divide your life into semesters, even when you’re not in school</a>.
<p/>
Put it all together, and my new goal is:
<p/>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"For the next three months, I will write for at least 30 minutes a day, at least 4 days a week."</blockquote>
<p/>
I'll report back in three months with how it went. Wish me luck!]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I made it a goal for myself when I first started this blog to post at least once a month. This condition was imposed with good intentions, to ensure that I would write consistently. This was to improve my writing, which was the main goal for starting the blog in the first place. But while it was well-intentioned, I don't believe it was the right move. It has been detrimental in two ways: first, it has increased unnecessary stress, and second, it has slowed down my writing pace. The obligation to post 'every month' is what causes the stress. By setting a time requirement, I have inadvertently set myself a deadline to post by the end of every month. Posting a day later (on the 1st) would still count as a failure in reaching my goal. This arbitrary deadline has made the approach of the end of the month something I dread, and to avoid feeling like I've failed in my goal I'll write something/anything to avoid that. This means the topics are chosen based on how quick and easy they would be to rush out, rather than what I am most interested in at the time. The second way that it impacted me is that whenever I thought of another topic I would like to write about, instead of starting on it right away I would only add them to my backlog. This provided me with a wide range of options at the end of the month (even if I would only select the 'easy' ones). As a result, I didn't write anything until the end of the month, which made me less consistent in my writing than I would have been. So what's the plan? The monthly restriction was in place for positive reasons, and despite slowing down my writing and raising my stress levels, it has also made sure that I update frequently. At this point the negatives outweigh the positives, so it's time to change. For more effective goal setting, a few things need to change. Let's start by using the SMART goal framework. This can be used to check that the goal is Specific, Measurable, Achievable, Relevant, and Time-Bound. Specific: For a goal to be specific, it needs to be able to answer questions such as "Who is responsible?" and "What needs to happen?". In this case, 'writing' needs to happen, by me specifically. Measurable: When a goal is quantifiable, we can measure the progress and also know that the goal has been achieved. Last time we tried measuring the number of posts completed in a month and it didn't work, so let's do a different time-based this time. Instead of measuring the number of posts, we will track the amount of time spent writing. Achievable: As tempting as it would be to declare that I should write every waking hour, that's not realistic. Considering the other obligations I have in my day-to-day life, an achievable amount of time I can set aside is 30 minutes minimum, ideally every day but in actuality at least 4 days a week. Of course, this may change if I need to, determining what is realistic may take some trial and error. Relevant: This is where we ask "Why?". If the overarching goal is to improve writing, then setting a goal to go horse riding won't help. But making it writing-related will - and for my scenario it doesn't have to be blog-specific writing, as my writing goals are wider than that. Time-Bound: This relates to making the goal measurable. All goals must end eventually, and having a time when even 'repeating' tasks are done means that they are much more likely to be completed. The time frame for this goal is the next three months, chosen thanks to this article: Why you should divide your life into semesters, even when you’re not in school. Put it all together, and my new goal is: "For the next three months, I will write for at least 30 minutes a day, at least 4 days a week." I'll report back in three months with how it went. Wish me luck!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Easy Video Editing with LosslessCut</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/31/LosslessCut.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Easy Video Editing with LosslessCut" /><published>2023-07-31T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-07-31T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/07/31/LosslessCut</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/31/LosslessCut.html"><![CDATA[Sometimes, I need an easy way to do basic video editing. It's nothing flashy. I just want to chop sections out, remove the dreaded <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Millennial_pause"target="_blank">'millennial pause'</a> from the start, and maybe stitch some files together. I don't need anything fancy, with no green screens or special effects required. There are lots of video editing programs that can do all that and more, but for this specific scenario, the easiest way that I have found to do video editing is by using <a href="https://www.mifi.no/losslesscut/"target="_blank">LosslessCut</a>.
<p/>
<img src="/img/posts/losslesscut.jpg" alt="Screenshot of LosslessCut software" style="width:100%">
<p/>
LosslessCut is a platform-independent program (yes it’s available for Linux), which is free and has a range of features, including:
<ul>
    <li>Lossless trimming and cutting of audio and video</li>
    <li>Merging clips in a single file</li>
    <li>Track extraction</li>
    <li>Convert files into different formats</li>
</ul>
<p/>
One of the main reasons I chose LosslessCut is due to its speed. Where most other video editors take a long time to render the final output, LosslessCut doesn’t transcode or re-encode the frames. This means that the video output will be the same quality as the input (hence the 'lossless' part of the name) and the whole process is much, much faster.
<p/>
I found that you can use this 'as-is', the settings are mostly fine to leave as default. The only change I would recommend is the precision of the segment cutting. The default settings cut at the ‘nearest keyframe’, which is determined by the encoding of the video file. It is possible to override this and trim the video to the precise moment required if the nearest keyframe is not near enough.
<p/>
Next time you need a basic video editor, give LosslessCut a try - what it lacks in advanced features it more than makes up for with its efficiency and ease of use. Happy editing!]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes, I need an easy way to do basic video editing. It's nothing flashy. I just want to chop sections out, remove the dreaded 'millennial pause' from the start, and maybe stitch some files together. I don't need anything fancy, with no green screens or special effects required. There are lots of video editing programs that can do all that and more, but for this specific scenario, the easiest way that I have found to do video editing is by using LosslessCut. LosslessCut is a platform-independent program (yes it’s available for Linux), which is free and has a range of features, including: Lossless trimming and cutting of audio and video Merging clips in a single file Track extraction Convert files into different formats One of the main reasons I chose LosslessCut is due to its speed. Where most other video editors take a long time to render the final output, LosslessCut doesn’t transcode or re-encode the frames. This means that the video output will be the same quality as the input (hence the 'lossless' part of the name) and the whole process is much, much faster. I found that you can use this 'as-is', the settings are mostly fine to leave as default. The only change I would recommend is the precision of the segment cutting. The default settings cut at the ‘nearest keyframe’, which is determined by the encoding of the video file. It is possible to override this and trim the video to the precise moment required if the nearest keyframe is not near enough. Next time you need a basic video editor, give LosslessCut a try - what it lacks in advanced features it more than makes up for with its efficiency and ease of use. Happy editing!]]></summary></entry></feed>