<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-08-31T17:21:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rebecca Platt</title><subtitle>Writing Stories and Code</subtitle><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Rules Are Not The Goal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/08/31/RulesAreNotTheGoal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rules Are Not The Goal" /><published>2023-08-31T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-08-31T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/08/31/RulesAreNotTheGoal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/08/31/RulesAreNotTheGoal.html"><![CDATA[I made it a goal for myself when I first started this blog to post at least once a month. This condition was imposed with good intentions, to ensure that I would write consistently. This was to improve my writing, which was the main goal for starting the blog in the first place. But while it was well-intentioned, I don't believe it was the right move. 
It has been detrimental in two ways: first, it has increased unnecessary stress, and second, it has slowed down my writing pace.
<p/>
The obligation to post 'every month' is what causes the stress. By setting a time requirement, I have inadvertently set myself a deadline to post by the end of every month. Posting a day later (on the 1st) would still count as a failure in reaching my goal. This arbitrary deadline has made the approach of the end of the month something I dread, and to avoid feeling like I've failed in my goal I'll write something/anything to avoid that. This means the topics are chosen based on how quick and easy they would be to rush out, rather than what I am most interested in at the time.
<p/>
The second way that it impacted me is that whenever I thought of another topic I would like to write about, instead of starting on it right away I would only add them to my backlog. This provided me with a wide range of options at the end of the month (even if I would only select the 'easy' ones). As a result, I didn't write anything until the end of the month, which made me less consistent in my writing than I would have been.
<p/>
So what's the plan? The monthly restriction was in place for positive reasons, and despite slowing down my writing and raising my stress levels, it has also made sure that I update frequently.
<p/>
At this point the negatives outweigh the positives, so it's time to change. For more effective goal setting, a few things need to change. Let's start by using the SMART goal framework. This can be used to check that the goal is Specific, Measurable, Achievable, Relevant, and Time-Bound.
<p/>
<b>Specific</b>: For a goal to be specific, it needs to be able to answer questions such as "Who is responsible?" and "What needs to happen?". In this case, 'writing' needs to happen, by me specifically.
<p/>
<b>Measurable</b>: When a goal is quantifiable, we can measure the progress and also know that the goal has been achieved. Last time we tried measuring the number of posts completed in a month and it didn't work, so let's do a different time-based this time. Instead of measuring the number of posts, we will track the amount of time spent writing.
<p/>
<b>Achievable</b>: As tempting as it would be to declare that I should write every waking hour, that's not realistic. Considering the other obligations I have in my day-to-day life, an achievable amount of time I can set aside is 30 minutes minimum, ideally every day but in actuality at least 4 days a week. Of course, this may change if I need to, determining what is realistic may take some trial and error.
<p/>
<b>Relevant</b>: This is where we ask "Why?". If the overarching goal is to improve writing, then setting a goal to go horse riding won't help. But making it writing-related will - and for my scenario it doesn't have to be blog-specific writing, as my writing goals are wider than that. 
<p/>
<b>Time-Bound</b>: This relates to making the goal measurable. All goals must end eventually, and having a time when even 'repeating' tasks are done means that they are much more likely to be completed. The time frame for this goal is the next three months, chosen thanks to this article: Why you should divide your life into semesters, even when you’re not in school (https://www.vox.com/even-better/23835758/divide-life-semesters-not-in-school-motivation-goals).
<p/>
Put it all together, and my new goal is:
<p/>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"For the next three months, I will write for at least 30 minutes a day, at least 4 days a week."</blockquote>
<p/>
I'll report back in three months with how it went. Wish me luck!]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I made it a goal for myself when I first started this blog to post at least once a month. This condition was imposed with good intentions, to ensure that I would write consistently. This was to improve my writing, which was the main goal for starting the blog in the first place. But while it was well-intentioned, I don't believe it was the right move. It has been detrimental in two ways: first, it has increased unnecessary stress, and second, it has slowed down my writing pace. The obligation to post 'every month' is what causes the stress. By setting a time requirement, I have inadvertently set myself a deadline to post by the end of every month. Posting a day later (on the 1st) would still count as a failure in reaching my goal. This arbitrary deadline has made the approach of the end of the month something I dread, and to avoid feeling like I've failed in my goal I'll write something/anything to avoid that. This means the topics are chosen based on how quick and easy they would be to rush out, rather than what I am most interested in at the time. The second way that it impacted me is that whenever I thought of another topic I would like to write about, instead of starting on it right away I would only add them to my backlog. This provided me with a wide range of options at the end of the month (even if I would only select the 'easy' ones). As a result, I didn't write anything until the end of the month, which made me less consistent in my writing than I would have been. So what's the plan? The monthly restriction was in place for positive reasons, and despite slowing down my writing and raising my stress levels, it has also made sure that I update frequently. At this point the negatives outweigh the positives, so it's time to change. For more effective goal setting, a few things need to change. Let's start by using the SMART goal framework. This can be used to check that the goal is Specific, Measurable, Achievable, Relevant, and Time-Bound. Specific: For a goal to be specific, it needs to be able to answer questions such as "Who is responsible?" and "What needs to happen?". In this case, 'writing' needs to happen, by me specifically. Measurable: When a goal is quantifiable, we can measure the progress and also know that the goal has been achieved. Last time we tried measuring the number of posts completed in a month and it didn't work, so let's do a different time-based this time. Instead of measuring the number of posts, we will track the amount of time spent writing. Achievable: As tempting as it would be to declare that I should write every waking hour, that's not realistic. Considering the other obligations I have in my day-to-day life, an achievable amount of time I can set aside is 30 minutes minimum, ideally every day but in actuality at least 4 days a week. Of course, this may change if I need to, determining what is realistic may take some trial and error. Relevant: This is where we ask "Why?". If the overarching goal is to improve writing, then setting a goal to go horse riding won't help. But making it writing-related will - and for my scenario it doesn't have to be blog-specific writing, as my writing goals are wider than that. Time-Bound: This relates to making the goal measurable. All goals must end eventually, and having a time when even 'repeating' tasks are done means that they are much more likely to be completed. The time frame for this goal is the next three months, chosen thanks to this article: Why you should divide your life into semesters, even when you’re not in school (https://www.vox.com/even-better/23835758/divide-life-semesters-not-in-school-motivation-goals). Put it all together, and my new goal is: "For the next three months, I will write for at least 30 minutes a day, at least 4 days a week." I'll report back in three months with how it went. Wish me luck!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Easy Video Editing with LosslessCut</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/31/LosslessCut.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Easy Video Editing with LosslessCut" /><published>2023-07-31T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-07-31T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/07/31/LosslessCut</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/31/LosslessCut.html"><![CDATA[Sometimes, I need an easy way to do basic video editing. It's nothing flashy. I just want to chop sections out, remove the dreaded <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Millennial_pause"target="_blank">'millennial pause'</a> from the start, and maybe stitch some files together. I don't need anything fancy, with no green screens or special effects required. There are lots of video editing programs that can do all that and more, but for this specific scenario, the easiest way that I have found to do video editing is by using <a href="https://www.mifi.no/losslesscut/"target="_blank">LosslessCut</a>.
<p/>
<img src="/img/posts/losslesscut.jpg" alt="Screenshot of LosslessCut software" style="width:100%">
<p/>
LosslessCut is a platform-independent program (yes it’s available for Linux), which is free and has a range of features, including:
<ul>
    <li>Lossless trimming and cutting of audio and video</li>
    <li>Merging clips in a single file</li>
    <li>Track extraction</li>
    <li>Convert files into different formats</li>
</ul>
<p/>
One of the main reasons I chose LosslessCut is due to its speed. Where most other video editors take a long time to render the final output, LosslessCut doesn’t transcode or re-encode the frames. This means that the video output will be the same quality as the input (hence the 'lossless' part of the name) and the whole process is much, much faster.
<p/>
I found that you can use this 'as-is', the settings are mostly fine to leave as default. The only change I would recommend is the precision of the segment cutting. The default settings cut at the ‘nearest keyframe’, which is determined by the encoding of the video file. It is possible to override this and trim the video to the precise moment required if the nearest keyframe is not near enough.
<p/>
Next time you need a basic video editor, give LosslessCut a try - what it lacks in advanced features it more than makes up for with its efficiency and ease of use. Happy editing!]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes, I need an easy way to do basic video editing. It's nothing flashy. I just want to chop sections out, remove the dreaded 'millennial pause' from the start, and maybe stitch some files together. I don't need anything fancy, with no green screens or special effects required. There are lots of video editing programs that can do all that and more, but for this specific scenario, the easiest way that I have found to do video editing is by using LosslessCut. LosslessCut is a platform-independent program (yes it’s available for Linux), which is free and has a range of features, including: Lossless trimming and cutting of audio and video Merging clips in a single file Track extraction Convert files into different formats One of the main reasons I chose LosslessCut is due to its speed. Where most other video editors take a long time to render the final output, LosslessCut doesn’t transcode or re-encode the frames. This means that the video output will be the same quality as the input (hence the 'lossless' part of the name) and the whole process is much, much faster. I found that you can use this 'as-is', the settings are mostly fine to leave as default. The only change I would recommend is the precision of the segment cutting. The default settings cut at the ‘nearest keyframe’, which is determined by the encoding of the video file. It is possible to override this and trim the video to the precise moment required if the nearest keyframe is not near enough. Next time you need a basic video editor, give LosslessCut a try - what it lacks in advanced features it more than makes up for with its efficiency and ease of use. Happy editing!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Choosing Topics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/06/29/ChoosingTopics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Choosing Topics" /><published>2023-06-29T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-06-29T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/06/29/ChoosingTopics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/06/29/ChoosingTopics.html"><![CDATA[There comes a time in every blog's life when we get meta with the topic and cover the age-old question; “What should I write about?”. Today is that day. Yet even though the post has barely started, there’s immediately a problem. The question is always a variation of “What should I write about?”
<p/>
<blockquote class="blockquote"><b>Should</b>: “used to indicate obligation, duty, or correctness, typically when criticizing someone's actions.”</blockquote>
<figcaption>— <a href="https://languages.oup.com/google-dictionary-en/" target="_blank">Oxford Languages</a></figcaption>
<p/>
By including the word ‘should’, what we are asking is ”What is the best and most correct topic for me to write about?” When written this way, it’s easier to see how this question puts a lot of undue stress on the person asking.
<p/>
<blockquote class="blockquote">“These types of statements can make you feel worried or anxious. They can also cause you to experience guilt or a sense of failure. Because you always think you "should" be doing something, you end up feeling as if you are constantly failing.”</blockquote>
<figcaption>— <a href="https://www.verywellmind.com/ten-cognitive-distortions-identified-in-cbt-22412" target="_blank">Verywell Mind</a></figcaption>
<p/>
A better version of this question is “What <i>could</i> I write about?”. To answer that I propose following the two methods outlined below. If you can follow both at the same time, fantastic. But if that’s too much pressure then keeping to one of them will also work fine.
<p/>
(Note: Though we are using writing as the framework, this advice also applies to any number of creative endeavours, including presenting, drawing, painting, filming, puppetry, and so on.)
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">Method One: Write what you know</h2>
<p/>
It’s generic advice I know, to say to cover what you know about. It also usually doesn’t work, because you’re left just as overwhelmed with intangible thoughts and concepts as you were before. Either you know lots of things but don’t know which of them would be ‘right’, or worse this is the moment when you have remembered absolutely nothing in your whole life and are drawing a blank.
<p/>
So first, we need to find out what we know.
<p/>
We do this by working to our strengths. Being humans, we are not great at starting from scratch. What are we good at though? Humans are good at spotting things, noticing the important aspects, and seeing patterns. We had to be to survive - seeing any dangers to avoid, and spotting resources at the same time. To highlight this, consider this exercise:
<p/>
Right now, without searching, name every dwarf in Snow White and The Seven Dwarfs. Unless you watched it recently, chances are that you will only remember a couple of them.
<br/>
Now try again, but this time while looking at this list of dwarf names:
<p/>
<img src="/img/posts/DwarfNames.jpg" alt="Word cloud of the names: Sneezy, Balin, Cranky, Gloin, Bofur, Kili, Grumpy, Fili, Doc, Flint, Gimli, Eitri, Bashful, Sleepy, Dopey, Mulch, Gleeful, Happy, Dozy, and Thorin."style="width:100%">
Chances are, you had much more success getting all seven names the second time.
<p/>
So how do we recreate this for any topic?
<p/>
First, get a blank notepad, document, or anywhere you can write freely. On there, write down every subject that you know anything about. It doesn’t matter how much or how little, just everything that comes to mind.
<p/>
From this page of subjects, choose one. It can be any of them - if one stands out to you then great, if none stands out then pick one at random.
<p/>
The next step is to write down everything you know about that chosen subject. Again we’re not self-censoring. It doesn’t matter how ‘basic’ or ‘boring’ the information is, get it all out on the page.
<p/>
Once we have things on the page, we can start to group things, and see if any interesting threads catch our eye. Put enough facts in a cohesive order, and just like that you have a workable structure for a blog post.
<p/>
<i>“But what if I barely wrote down anything?”</i> 
<br/>
Sometimes we don’t have full creative freedom to choose the topic as it has been dictated by someone else, and we have to talk about it anyway. Other times we do want to cover a topic, but we aren’t as well versed in it and there isn’t enough information to work with.
<p/>
In this scenario, when you simply don’t know enough, it’s time to learn about the subject. Using the above exercise we can see the gaps in our knowledge, so now it’s time to fill them.
<p/>
One way to do this is to write everything out on a page, again. But instead of writing what you know, write what your questions are about the topic. What do you want to know? This is for your viewing only, so feel free to ask any questions that you want. Use these questions as a guide to your studies.
<p/>
Learning about the topic more will also go a long way to help with any feelings of imposter syndrome (which is a topic I may cover in a later blog post).
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">Method Two: Write what you are interested in</h2>
<p/>
When choosing between multiple potential topics, always err on the side of the most interesting one. By this I mean the one most of interest to you, not the one you think is ‘objectively’ most interesting. I once attended a two-hour-long worm farm seminar (it’s a long story), and beforehand I was dreading going - it felt safe to assume I was about to be very bored. Instead, it ended up being a surprisingly enthralling experience and I learned more about worms than I ever thought I would, all because the person giving the presentation was that engrossed in the topic himself. We respond to the emotions of other people more than we realise. Seeing someone bored is boring, and seeing someone excited is exciting.
<p/>
If you must write about a topic that is not of interest to you, then the next best step is to find a way to care about the subject. Is there an aspect of the topic that you are more interested in? Can you change the ‘angle’ of focus to that?
<p/>
Finally, writing about a topic of interest will make the whole writing process more fun. Too often we focus on the outcome, on the finished piece. “Will this be any good?” or “Will anyone care?”, we worry about the reception, or about what’s next, and many, many other things besides. Take the pressure off the outcome, and look at the process instead. You have to be there for the process anyway. The enjoyment you feel during writing will have an impact on both the draft and final products, and it will reflect through the writing in a million different ways. And in the very unlikely worst-case scenario, where everything you have written is utterly unpublishable - at least you had fun while writing it.]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There comes a time in every blog's life when we get meta with the topic and cover the age-old question; “What should I write about?”. Today is that day. Yet even though the post has barely started, there’s immediately a problem. The question is always a variation of “What should I write about?” Should: “used to indicate obligation, duty, or correctness, typically when criticizing someone's actions.” — Oxford Languages By including the word ‘should’, what we are asking is ”What is the best and most correct topic for me to write about?” When written this way, it’s easier to see how this question puts a lot of undue stress on the person asking. “These types of statements can make you feel worried or anxious. They can also cause you to experience guilt or a sense of failure. Because you always think you "should" be doing something, you end up feeling as if you are constantly failing.” — Verywell Mind A better version of this question is “What could I write about?”. To answer that I propose following the two methods outlined below. If you can follow both at the same time, fantastic. But if that’s too much pressure then keeping to one of them will also work fine. (Note: Though we are using writing as the framework, this advice also applies to any number of creative endeavours, including presenting, drawing, painting, filming, puppetry, and so on.) Method One: Write what you know It’s generic advice I know, to say to cover what you know about. It also usually doesn’t work, because you’re left just as overwhelmed with intangible thoughts and concepts as you were before. Either you know lots of things but don’t know which of them would be ‘right’, or worse this is the moment when you have remembered absolutely nothing in your whole life and are drawing a blank. So first, we need to find out what we know. We do this by working to our strengths. Being humans, we are not great at starting from scratch. What are we good at though? Humans are good at spotting things, noticing the important aspects, and seeing patterns. We had to be to survive - seeing any dangers to avoid, and spotting resources at the same time. To highlight this, consider this exercise: Right now, without searching, name every dwarf in Snow White and The Seven Dwarfs. Unless you watched it recently, chances are that you will only remember a couple of them. Now try again, but this time while looking at this list of dwarf names: Chances are, you had much more success getting all seven names the second time. So how do we recreate this for any topic? First, get a blank notepad, document, or anywhere you can write freely. On there, write down every subject that you know anything about. It doesn’t matter how much or how little, just everything that comes to mind. From this page of subjects, choose one. It can be any of them - if one stands out to you then great, if none stands out then pick one at random. The next step is to write down everything you know about that chosen subject. Again we’re not self-censoring. It doesn’t matter how ‘basic’ or ‘boring’ the information is, get it all out on the page. Once we have things on the page, we can start to group things, and see if any interesting threads catch our eye. Put enough facts in a cohesive order, and just like that you have a workable structure for a blog post. “But what if I barely wrote down anything?” Sometimes we don’t have full creative freedom to choose the topic as it has been dictated by someone else, and we have to talk about it anyway. Other times we do want to cover a topic, but we aren’t as well versed in it and there isn’t enough information to work with. In this scenario, when you simply don’t know enough, it’s time to learn about the subject. Using the above exercise we can see the gaps in our knowledge, so now it’s time to fill them. One way to do this is to write everything out on a page, again. But instead of writing what you know, write what your questions are about the topic. What do you want to know? This is for your viewing only, so feel free to ask any questions that you want. Use these questions as a guide to your studies. Learning about the topic more will also go a long way to help with any feelings of imposter syndrome (which is a topic I may cover in a later blog post). Method Two: Write what you are interested in When choosing between multiple potential topics, always err on the side of the most interesting one. By this I mean the one most of interest to you, not the one you think is ‘objectively’ most interesting. I once attended a two-hour-long worm farm seminar (it’s a long story), and beforehand I was dreading going - it felt safe to assume I was about to be very bored. Instead, it ended up being a surprisingly enthralling experience and I learned more about worms than I ever thought I would, all because the person giving the presentation was that engrossed in the topic himself. We respond to the emotions of other people more than we realise. Seeing someone bored is boring, and seeing someone excited is exciting. If you must write about a topic that is not of interest to you, then the next best step is to find a way to care about the subject. Is there an aspect of the topic that you are more interested in? Can you change the ‘angle’ of focus to that? Finally, writing about a topic of interest will make the whole writing process more fun. Too often we focus on the outcome, on the finished piece. “Will this be any good?” or “Will anyone care?”, we worry about the reception, or about what’s next, and many, many other things besides. Take the pressure off the outcome, and look at the process instead. You have to be there for the process anyway. The enjoyment you feel during writing will have an impact on both the draft and final products, and it will reflect through the writing in a million different ways. And in the very unlikely worst-case scenario, where everything you have written is utterly unpublishable - at least you had fun while writing it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do’s and Don’ts of Presentation Slides</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/31/PresentationSlideDesign.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do’s and Don’ts of Presentation Slides" /><published>2023-05-31T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-05-31T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/05/31/PresentationSlideDesign</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/31/PresentationSlideDesign.html"><![CDATA[If you have ever worried about not knowing how to give a good presentation, please know that it is not your fault.
<p/>
I have been in the audience for quite a few presentations over the years, and while there have been a few great ones here and there, I can’t say the same for most of them. Some presentations were immediately forgettable at best, while others were laid out in such a confusing way that by the end of it I still had no idea what they were talking about.
<p/>
I don't blame these presenters however. The vast majority of people are never taught how to give presentations. We get taught how to write, how to code, and many other skills required for our roles; but when it comes to presenting information in a clear and effective manner we are generally left to wing it. 
<p/>
The good news is, by taking the time to read this (and/or by searching for other tips online), you’re already one step closer to giving a great presentation. The fact you’re looking to improve shows that you care about delivering your topic well, and that alone will make it a better presentation. 
<p/>
In this post, I will only be covering tips for designing the layouts of your slides. All other aspects of presentations (for example; organising the content or managing nerves) will be covered in later posts. We are starting with how the slides look, because even the design can have a huge impact on the audience’s initial impression and expectations.
<p/>
A lot of the advice in this post is taken from the below talk by Damian Conway - so of you prefer a video format instead, I highly recommend watching that.
<p/>
<iframe class="youtube-video" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/W_i_DrWic88" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p/>

One final disclaimer: Technically, all the advice given here is subjective and simply what I find to be effective. You can choose to follow all, some, or even none of it. That said, here are the “Do’s and Don’ts” of slide design.
<p/>
<h1>Do:</h1>
<p/>
<h4>✔ Only have one point per slide</h4>
You can only talk about one point at a time. That means that everything on screen will either help or hinder you to convey that point effectively. Having more slides with a single point on each of them is more effective than listing multiple points on the same slide.
<p/>
<img src="/img/posts/AllOnOneSlide.png" alt="Single slide with static placeholder text over three lines" style="width:49%">
<img src="/img/posts/SeparateSlides.gif" alt="Multiple slides with the same text but each line is shown in succession" style="width:49%">
<blockquote class="blockquote"style="text-align: center;">Which of these do you think is more engaging?</blockquote>

<p/>
<h4>✔ Use pictures instead of text where possible</h4>
They are worth a thousand words after all - images are more dynamic and engaging that plain text alone can every be. When using pictures, make sure:
<ul>
    <li>The images are high quality. Blurry and pixelated images will distract from your message, and it can look like you didn’t care enough to find a better quality image. (If it looks like the presenter doesn’t care, why should the audience?)</li>
    <li>There are no watermarks on the images.</li>
    <li>Fill the whole slide with the image when possible, don’t just drop the image in the centre.</li>
</ul>
<p/>
If it’s an image with a transparent background (or if it doesn’t make sense to fill the whole slide with it, align it in the centre with these shortcuts:
<p/>
<a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/align-and-arrange-objects-on-a-slide-5f961535-a2ae-4914-a24a-94c669903ae3"target="_blank">For PowerPoint:</a>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
    <ol>
        <li>
            Select the objects you want to align.
            <br/>Press Shift to select multiple objects.
        </li>
        <li>Select <b>Picture format > Align</b> and select how you want to align them:
        <br/>
        <ul>
            <li>Align Left, Align Center, or Align Right</li>
            <li>Align Top, Align Middle, or Align Bottom</li>
            <li>Distribute Horizontally or Distribute Vertically</li>
        </ul>
        </li>
    </ol>
</blockquote>
<a href="https://www.canva.com/en_au/help/layer-group-align/"target="_blank">For Canva:</a>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
    <ol>
        <li>Click the element you want to edit.</li>
        <li>To select multiple elements, hold Shift on your keyboard, and click to add other elements to the selection.</li>
        <li>On the toolbar above the editor, click Position, and refer below depending on what you want to do. If you don’t see it, click the button first.</li>
    </ol>
<b>Aligning elements</b>
<ul>
    <li><b>Align to page.</b> These options become available when there’s only one element selected. They use your design page as the point of reference for alignment.</li>
    <li><b>Align elements.</b> These appear when you have more than one element selected. They use the positions of all selected elements as the basis for alignment.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
If you can’t use an image and plan to use text, then…
<p/>
<h4>✔ Increase the font size</h4>
If you have an in person audience, 60pt is the minimum font size that I recommend. After all, when you are presenting to a larger audience, the text needs to be clearly visible from the very back. If you (like most people these days) have an online audience, I can understand why you might think that there would be more flexibility, and that we could allow smaller fonts -  but no, it should still be 60pt at least. The reasons are that:
<ul>
    <li>Accessibility should still be considered - you don’t know how good or bad the eyesight of everyone in your audience is.</li>
    <li>You do not have control over what device they are using - they could be watching on a smaller device like their phone.</li>
</ul>
Finally, smaller fonts should also be avoided as  they can tempt you to put more information on the screen at once, creating a wall of text which will distract and dilute from the point you are making.
<p/>
<h4>✔ Use accessible colours</h4>
Projectors are evil, and screens can be evil too. When presenting in a new location, will you know what the technology set up will be? What do you do if you have to (as an example) present on a projector that only works in greyscale? If you ensure that you use a more accessible array of colours with a decent contrast between them, you will have slides that will work with any problems that the projectors and screens can throw at you (as well as being inclusive to more of your audience members!). 
<ul>
    <li>Higher contrast (such as white on black for example) almost always helps.</li>
    <li>Cyan, dark blue, yellow, and red are all effective colours that tend to work even for those with colour impairment.
    </li>
</ul>
There are a number of tools available for you to test your slides level of contrast and accessibility in general. Some that I recommend are:
<ul>
    <li><a href="https://webaim.org/resources/contrastchecker/"target="_blank">WebAIM: Contrast Checker</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/make-your-powerpoint-presentations-accessible-to-people-with-disabilities-6f7772b2-2f33-4bd2-8ca7-dae3b2b3ef25"target="_blank">“Make your PowerPoint presentations accessible to people with disabilities” by Microsoft</a></li>
</ul>
<p/>
<h4>✔ Have a consistent style</h4>
Having a consistent theme across your slides shows the audience that you care, and also implies that the talk you are giving is somewhat cohesive. Having half the slides in one design style and the rest in a completely different style may confuse the audience, as if you have stitched two separate topics together Frankenstein-style.
<p/>
<h4>✔ Use multiple levels of differentiation when showing complex data (like code)</h4>
For this one, I’m going to refer to the video I mentioned at the start - starting at timestamp <a href="https://youtu.be/W_i_DrWic88?t=4193"target="_blank">1:09:53</a>:
<iframe class="youtube-video" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/W_i_DrWic88?start=4193" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p/>
<hr>
<p/>
<h1>Don’t:</h1>
<p/>
<h4>❌ Have a wall of text up there. Not even with bullet points.</h4>
People will stop listening and start reading instead. If they can understand the entirety of the contents of the talk from reading the slides, then why are you up there presenting? Also people can generally read faster than you talk. Letting them read all the content also means making them wait until you’re finished speaking to get to the next slide, which can cause frustration or boredom.
<p/>
<h4>❌ Put your logo on every slide</h4>
Elements that stay in the same place on every slide attract attention - but if those elements are not related to the point you are making at that time they attract it away from what you’re saying. Also it looks like advertising, which people often don’t like.
<p/>
If you have/want to include your company logo / social links / other information like that, then put them on the first and last slide. Having them on those slides will still ensure that the people see them, but won’t take away from the talk itself.
<p/>
<h4>❌ Show a slide counter</h4>
Or bar, or anything that shows the progression of time.
<p/>
People will watch that instead, and then they can’t help but plan what they are doing next (such as their next meeting). Which means they’re no longer paying attention to your talk.
<p/>
<blockquote class="blockquote" style="text-align: center;">When they open PowerPoint and you see “Slide 1 of 256”</blockquote>
<img src="/img/posts/elisa-ventur.jpg" alt="Photo of person looking at laptop in despair" style="width:100%">
<blockquote class="blockquote" style="text-align: center;">Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/es/@elisa_ventur?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText"target="_blank">Elisa Ventur</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/yjHh4JpZQT8?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText"target="_blank">Unsplash</a></blockquote>
<p/>
<h4>❌ Use a laser pointer</h4>
Not only does it do a terrible job at highlighting parts of the slide for in person audiences, it doesn’t work at all for the online audience.
<p/>
The people who can see it will show you that humans are actually cats - they will watch the moving light and be distracted from what you’re saying.
<p/>
If you feel that you need to use one, that means that your slides need updating. Either your slides are not already clearly highlighting the current point being made, or more likely you have more than one point on your slide.
<p/>
<h4>❌ Design the slides to be used as notes afterwards</h4>
Slides are there to help supplement your talk, not to contain its entirety.
<p/>
If you want to send the audience your notes of the points covered afterwards, write a separate document to share with them instead. They will appreciate having an easy to read document instead of having to flick through presentation slides.
<p/>
<hr>
<p/>
Follow these tips for your presentations, and you will be well on your way to delivering a more impactful, effective, and interesting talk.If you know any other tips and tricks, share and let everyone know in the comments section below.]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you have ever worried about not knowing how to give a good presentation, please know that it is not your fault. I have been in the audience for quite a few presentations over the years, and while there have been a few great ones here and there, I can’t say the same for most of them. Some presentations were immediately forgettable at best, while others were laid out in such a confusing way that by the end of it I still had no idea what they were talking about. I don't blame these presenters however. The vast majority of people are never taught how to give presentations. We get taught how to write, how to code, and many other skills required for our roles; but when it comes to presenting information in a clear and effective manner we are generally left to wing it. The good news is, by taking the time to read this (and/or by searching for other tips online), you’re already one step closer to giving a great presentation. The fact you’re looking to improve shows that you care about delivering your topic well, and that alone will make it a better presentation. In this post, I will only be covering tips for designing the layouts of your slides. All other aspects of presentations (for example; organising the content or managing nerves) will be covered in later posts. We are starting with how the slides look, because even the design can have a huge impact on the audience’s initial impression and expectations. A lot of the advice in this post is taken from the below talk by Damian Conway - so of you prefer a video format instead, I highly recommend watching that.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is This Optimal?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/03/IsThisOptimal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is This Optimal?" /><published>2023-05-03T20:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-05-03T20:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/05/03/IsThisOptimal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/03/IsThisOptimal.html"><![CDATA[Recently, I've been thinking about optimisation and how I can go about optimising my life. Possibly as a way of procrastinating on actually doing the tasks on my to-do list; and probably also as a way of attempting to gain a sense of control in this odd reality.
<p/>
Anyway, with the sheer <a href="https://time.com/3859238/career-productivity-optimize/" target="_blank">number</a> of <a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/living/8-time-management-hacks-to-optimize-your-life-in-and/322152" target="_blank">articles</a> on <a href="https://www.calendar.com/blog/14-calendar-hacks-to-help-you-optimize-and-save-time/" target="_blank">optimisation</a> out <a href="https://hbr.org/2021/02/4-ways-to-get-more-done-in-less-time" target="_blank">there</a>, it's reasonable to assume that I'm not the only one thinking about this.
  
<p/>
<blockquote class="tiktok-embed" cite="https://www.tiktok.com/@nestingyourlife/video/7206084704301468974" data-video-id="7206084704301468974" style="max-width: 605px;min-width: 325px;" > <section> <a target="_blank" title="@nestingyourlife" href="https://www.tiktok.com/@nestingyourlife?refer=embed">@nestingyourlife</a> Replying to @rosebudandcae a tale as old as time <a title="organization" target="_blank" href="https://www.tiktok.com/tag/organization?refer=embed">#organization</a> <a title="homeorganizing" target="_blank" href="https://www.tiktok.com/tag/homeorganizing?refer=embed">#homeorganizing</a> <a title="executivedysfuntion" target="_blank" href="https://www.tiktok.com/tag/executivedysfuntion?refer=embed">#executivedysfuntion</a> <a title="neurospicy" target="_blank" href="https://www.tiktok.com/tag/neurospicy?refer=embed">#neurospicy</a> <a target="_blank" title="♬ Requiem, KV 626 - 8. Lacrimosa - Mozart" href="https://www.tiktok.com/music/Requiem-KV-626-8-Lacrimosa-6726459984999122945?refer=embed">♬ Requiem, KV 626 - 8. Lacrimosa - Mozart</a> </section> </blockquote> <script async src="https://www.tiktok.com/embed.js"></script>
<blockquote class="blockquote"style="text-align: center;">and tiktoks too, of course.</blockquote>

<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">What Is Optimisation?</h2>
<p/>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"The action of making the best or most effective use of a situation or resource."</blockquote>
<figcaption>— <a href="https://www.oed.com/" target="_blank">Oxford Dictionaries</a></figcaption>
<p/>
How people try to optimise their lives depends on the way they interpret that definition. (For example; is the resource to measure ‘time’ or ‘effort’?) the variations of optimisation that I tend to see happen are:
<p/>
<ul>
    <li>Complete Tasks Perfectly</li>
    <li>Only Complete Favoured Tasks</li>
    <li>Only Complete Important Tasks</li>
    <li>Complete Tasks Faster</li>
</ul>

<h2 class="section-heading">Complete Tasks Perfectly</h2>
<p/>
If we decide that the resource that we should optimise is the effort that we put into doing tasks, then it follows that we must do the task perfectly on the first attempt. After all, re-doing the task would at least double the amount of effort used. Depending on how much pressure you put on yourself, this can very easily lead to perfectionism.
<p/>
As an example of perfectionism, I have a confession: I'm struggling to write this because I'm trying to determine the most optimal way to phrase every word, even when writing the first draft. When you argue that it's optimal to do a task once, the 'correct' way, it can lead to never starting on the task. Because you're now too busy figuring out what exactly the perfect way to do it is (as if that exists). I wrote this article on my phone but almost didn't start it at all. I thought the 'better' way would be to do it on my laptop so I could use a keyboard to type more comfortably. If I had given in to that line of thought, by the time I had turned on the laptop I would have decided that a different task was a more 'optimal' use of my time. (The fact that the ‘more optimal’ task is always one that requires less effort from me (like watching videos) never seems to come up consciously in my decision-making process. Weird that.)
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">Only Complete Favoured Tasks</h2>
<p/>
What if optimising means only focusing on the tasks and goals that make you happy? Surely one of the underlying reasons that we pursue optimisation is to increase happiness in our lives. So we ask ourselves if a task sparks joy, and only prioritise it if it does.
<p/>
The problem with this approach arises when we are weighing between a short-term and a long-term goal. If you deprioritise any tasks that are not immediately rewarding, what about the smaller tasks that build towards long-term goals? For example, writing this is difficult now, even though I know it's working towards the goal of writing a blog. Following this method, I would have already stopped writing at this point. Or to put it another way, it’s often the difference between exercising (short-term pain, long-term gain) or not exercising (short-term gain, long-term pain).
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">Only Complete Important Tasks</h2>
<p/>
In this approach, we are again optimising by prioritising tasks. This is where existential questions may appear:
<br/>
"What do I want to do with my life?"
<br/>
"Do I want to achieve goal x or y?"
<br/>
"Which dream job is the one true dream job?"
<p/>
Alternatively, we may not group tasks by their relation to a goal and instead look at which tasks we can remove completely. We try to use algorithms to make decisions for us or remove small daily decisions altogether by always re-wearing the same outfit (If it works for <a href="https://www.inc-aus.com/craig-bloem/this-1-unusual-habit-helped-make-mark-zuckerberg-steve-jobs-dr-dre-successful.html" target="_blank">successful people</a> it should work for us too, right?).
<p/>
Delegation of everything not deemed optimal only works if you have a lot of money to throw at the problem. Even then, I suspect it doesn't fix it 100%. (But I'm more than willing to become rich to test that theory.) Unfortunately, there are aspects of life that we cannot avoid, like death and taxes. So instead, we try to do everything in a prioritised manner, with the sinking feeling that we will never clear our to-do lists because we're only human (and cloning ourselves à la the 2018 film Replicas isn't possible yet).
<p/>
<img src="/img/posts/Replicas.jpg" alt="Poster of Replicas (2018)" style="width:100%">
<blockquote class="blockquote"style="text-align: center;">Hopefully the real-life version will have better reviews.</blockquote>
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">Complete Tasks Faster</h2>
<p/>
What if I want to have an amazing schedule so that I can fit in as many tasks as possible? That way, I could complete everything that I wanted to, not just the tasks at the top of my list.
<p/>
Surely one of the many calendar and organisation software things will solve my problem—oh, it could even use AI to determine the best time to do everything!
<p/>
Usually when we’re thinking this, we believe that we have been getting ‘nothing’ done - so we try to overcorrect. We schedule every second of our day to the breaking point. We know that we need breaks, but when it comes to how many and how often, we tend to underestimate. Then when it’s time to estimate the amount of time for the task itself, we again struggle to determine how much time it requires. A few people may manage to follow this new schedule for a short time, but many will build the ‘perfect’ calendar and then immediately not follow it. This can be due to many reasons, including forgetting that you have good days and bad days and planning as if every day was a good day.
<p/>
So if trying to complete tasks perfectly doesn't lead to being optimal, and being ruthless with decision-making doesn't either, and neither does trying to cram in as many tasks as efficiently as possible... then what does?
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">Why Do We Want To Optimise Everything?</h2>
<p/>
Instead of providing you with a non-existent magical solution, I ask you to consider the following instead: Is the dream of optimisation just another need being drilled into us by our environments?
<p/>
There are multi-billion-dollar industries that work to convince us that we are not good enough in a wide range of attributes. They have products to sell, and one way to do so is by convincing you that 1) you have a problem, and 2) this time, their product will solve your problem. Buy their self-improvement course/book/software, and all your dreams could come true. This reminds me of a story called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anekdote_zur_Senkung_der_Arbeitsmoral" target="_blank">"Anecdote Concerning the Lowering of Productivity" by Heinrich Böll</a>:
<p/>
<hr>
<br/>
<i>(As the original is in German, below is <a href="https://medium.com/life-lemons/what-you-can-learn-from-a-mexican-fisherman-a8334882204c" target="_blank">a translation.</a>)</i>
<p/>
<blockquote class="blockquote">An American investment banker was taking a much-needed vacation in a small coastal Mexican village when a small boat with just one fisherman docked. The boat had several large, fresh fish in it.
<p/>
The investment banker was impressed by the quality of the fish and asked the Mexican how long it took to catch them.
<p/>
The Mexican replied, “Only a little while.”
<p/>
The banker then asked why he didn’t stay out longer and catch more fish?
<p/>
The Mexican fisherman replied he had enough to support his family’s immediate needs.
<p/>
The American then asked: “But what do you do with the rest of your time?”
<p/>
The Mexican fisherman replied, “I sleep late, fish a little, play with my children, take siesta with my wife, stroll into the village each evening where I sip wine and play guitar with my amigos: I have a full and busy life, señor.”
<p/>
The investment banker scoffed: “I am an Ivy League MBA, and I could help you. You could spend more time fishing and with the proceeds buy a bigger boat, and with the proceeds from the bigger boat you could buy several boats until eventually, you would have a whole fleet of fishing boats. Instead of selling your catch to the middleman, you could sell directly to the processor, eventually opening your own cannery. You could control the product, processing and distribution.”
<p/>
Then he added: “Of course, you would need to leave this small coastal fishing village and move to Mexico City where you would run your growing enterprise.”
<p/>
The Mexican fisherman asked, “But señor, how long will this all take?”
<p/>
To which the American replied: “15–20 years.”
<p/>
“But what then?” asked the Mexican.
<p/>
The American laughed and said, “That’s the best part. When the time is right you would announce an IPO and sell your company stock to the public and become very rich. You could make millions.”
<p/>
“Millions, señor? Then what?”
<p/>
To which the investment banker replied: “Then you would retire. You could move to a small coastal fishing village where you would sleep late, fish a little, play with your kids, take siesta with your wife, stroll to the village in the evenings where you could sip wine and play your guitar with your amigos.”</blockquote>
<p/>
<hr>
<p/>
I don't think we can ever be 100% optimised. There's always a way to save more time, delegate a task to others, or re-evaluate what is truly important. It could be me being cynical, but it does feel like just another way that we are being tricked into wanting more and into being unhappy with who we are. All so we'll pay for the next magic calendar software that will fix our problems this time.
<p/>
Maybe it's truly optimal to assess where you are now, and instead of trying to overhaul every aspect, simply accept it. Make changes if they seem like a good idea, but do it in moderation. Instead of going from one extreme to another, gradual changes over time have a significantly greater success rate in the long run. If anything is worth doing, it's worth doing as badly and repeatedly as needed. Above all, try not to base your entire sense of worth on being optimised. Next time you catch yourself thinking "How should I improve this?", also ask yourself, "Why do I want to improve this? This reviewing I'm doing—is this optimal?"
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently, I've been thinking about optimisation and how I can go about optimising my life. Possibly as a way of procrastinating on actually doing the tasks on my to-do list; and probably also as a way of attempting to gain a sense of control in this odd reality. Anyway, with the sheer number of articles on optimisation out there, it's reasonable to assume that I'm not the only one thinking about this. @nestingyourlife Replying to @rosebudandcae a tale as old as time #organization #homeorganizing #executivedysfuntion #neurospicy ♬ Requiem, KV 626 - 8. Lacrimosa - Mozart and tiktoks too, of course.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why You Need A Password Manager</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/03/29/Why-You-Need-A-Password-Manager.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why You Need A Password Manager" /><published>2023-03-29T20:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-03-29T20:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/03/29/Why-You-Need-A-Password-Manager</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/03/29/Why-You-Need-A-Password-Manager.html"><![CDATA[Are you someone who would call themselves "not technical"? Do you know a "technical" person? Do they keep trying to convince you to use a password manager, but you aren't quite sure what that is? Then read on!
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">What is it?</h2>
<p/>
The name gives it away - it's a tool that you can use to manage your passwords, by being a secure location to store your account details.
<p/>
It may help to think of it like the contacts list on your phone. You don't remember every person's phone number, because you don't have to. You can just click the person's name, and their number is ready for you to use.
<p/>
With a password manager, you don't have to remember every password because it's stored with other details that make it easier for you to search, like the URL and your username.
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">Why do you need it?</h2>
<p/>
Apart from being more convenient (as described above), there are several other reasons to use a password manager - such as increased security, organization, and efficiency.
<p/>
<h4>Security</h4>
Most people are aware that using the same password on multiple sites is bad because if one site is hacked, then your accounts on other sites are at risk. (This is called a credential stuffing attack.) But most people are also human and can not remember unique passwords for every account they have. So we relax, convince ourselves it's fine, reuse the same password everywhere and put ourselves at risk.
<p/>
With a password manager, you can remove that risk without taking on the heavy mental load. Using a manager means you only have to remember one password (the master password for the manager), and then you can use unique passwords for all your accounts easily.
<p/>
Password managers can also generate new passwords for you to use, ensuring that they are stronger and more unique than "Password1" or "YourNormalPassword+1."
<p/>
The stronger the password is, the longer it will take to crack. If you want to see how long it would take to crack different passwords, check out: <a href="https://www.passwordmonster.com/" target="_blank">Password Monster</a>.
<p/>
Most password managers can also provide a review of your current accounts and passwords. With this, they give you a report of which accounts have been breached, which accounts use the same password as others, and other relevant information to let you know which ones may be at risk and need to be changed.
<p/>
They can also help protect you against phishing scams. Phishing scams are a type of attack where the scammer pretends to be the actual site you want to use. They normally work by sending you emails or texts saying you need to do something on the site (and urgently, for example, an email stating “You just sent a large amount of money to this other place” will make you panic and want to log on to cancel that), and then providing you with a link to a site which looks almost identical to the actual site to get your account details. Password managers can help because it doesn't matter how good the fake site is (and presumably it is good if you've gotten as far as trying to enter your details), the password manager won't auto-populate the details if the URL of the site is wrong.
<p/>
You can also use a password manager to securely share passwords. If you need to give your login details to someone else, rather than sending them the password in a way that could be read by others instead you can use a password manager to create a secure link to share instead. By sharing details this way you can also control other aspects such as how long they can view the password, and whether the link will only work for them or anyone with a copy of the link.
<p/>
<h4>Organization</h4>
Password managers allow you to keep all your passwords organized in one place. This means that you don't have to worry about forgetting where you stored a password or which password you used for a particular account. It’s also great for keeping track of which sites you already have an account for, so you don’t try to sign up to the same site twice.
<p/>
<h4>Efficiency</h4>
A password manager can also save you time by automatically filling in your login details for you. This can be especially helpful if you have multiple accounts to manage or if you switch between devices.
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">Does it mean I can be hacked once, and they get everything?</h2>
<p/>
Technically yes, but this is still a safer method than reusing passwords, and a more practical method than having you try to memorise a large number of complex passwords.
<p/>
No password storage method is without risk - reusing has a greater risk of being cracked, and remembering everything has a greater risk of you forgetting them.
<p/>
Password managers are more practical (meaning you're more likely to keep using them because they're not awful to deal with), and also they're more secure than most websites.
<p/>
There are a lot of in-depth articles about <a href="https://cybernews.com/best-password-managers/how-do-password-managers-work/" target="_blank">how password managers work</a>, but the gist is that they work in such a way that even they don't know your master password, meaning that even they can't get access to your passwords because everything is encrypted. So even if someone does get into their servers and steal your data, they still have to crack your master password first.
<p/>
You can keep everything even more secure by enabling <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/t/twofactor-authentication-2fa.asp#:~:text=Key%20Takeaways-,Two%2Dfactor%20authentication%20(2FA)%20is%20a%20security%20system%20that,fingerprint%2C%20face%2C%20or%20retina." target="_blank">two-factor authentication</a> as well. Then even if they manage to get your master password, they would still be prevented access unless they also had the secondary identification required.
<p/>
What all this means is that yes if they get in they would have access to all your accounts - but they would have a much harder time getting access in the first place.
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">What to look for?</h2>
<p/>
<h4>Usability</h4> 
Most password managers give a free trial period, so use them to see how comfortable you are with using them. The majority work in the same way (for example with browser extensions), but you may find some make more sense to you than others. It’s worth taking the time to determine how easy it is for you to use at the start, because if some aspect of the process frustrates you then you’re more likely to stop using it and end up back at square one. Test it by seeing how easy it is to add a new password to the manager, how easy it is to use the manager to log into a website of your choice, and also how well it works across all your devices (as most password managers also have an app so you can access it via your phone as well as your desktop).
<p/>
<h4>Pricing</h4>
Most managers only cost a few dollars a month, but it’s still worth doing a comparison to ensure you’re paying an amount that you are comfortable with.
<p/>
<h4>Reputation</h4> 
When it comes to security it’s best to think about what happens ‘when’ you get breached, not ‘if’ you will. The same thought applies to password managers. See if they have a history of breaches, and if so how the company responds to them. Being breached previously is not necessarily a deal breaker, but how they respond to it may be. If they are slow to let users know about a breach (so that users can update their passwords) or try to cover it up , then that password manager is probably not the place to trust with your credentials. For example, in late 2022 LastPass had a severe data breach and mishandled it to the point that they lost a lot of peoples’ trust and there were a lot of calls for people to <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/daveywinder/2023/03/03/why-you-should-stop-using-lastpass-after-new-hack-method-update/?sh=44143d4628fc" target="_blank">move to different password managers instead</a>.
<p/>
Using a password manager is not only convenient, but it’s also essential for online security. It helps to eliminate the risk of using the same password across multiple accounts and increases the strength of passwords by generating new ones. They allow you to be more organized and efficient by keeping all passwords in one secure location and auto-filling them in when needed. While no method of password storage is completely risk-free, password managers are a practical and secure solution to the problem. That’s why the “technical” people you know want you to use one.]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Are you someone who would call themselves "not technical"? Do you know a "technical" person? Do they keep trying to convince you to use a password manager, but you aren't quite sure what that is? Then read on! What is it? The name gives it away - it's a tool that you can use to manage your passwords, by being a secure location to store your account details. It may help to think of it like the contacts list on your phone. You don't remember every person's phone number, because you don't have to. You can just click the person's name, and their number is ready for you to use. With a password manager, you don't have to remember every password because it's stored with other details that make it easier for you to search, like the URL and your username. Why do you need it? Apart from being more convenient (as described above), there are several other reasons to use a password manager - such as increased security, organization, and efficiency. Security Most people are aware that using the same password on multiple sites is bad because if one site is hacked, then your accounts on other sites are at risk. (This is called a credential stuffing attack.) But most people are also human and can not remember unique passwords for every account they have. So we relax, convince ourselves it's fine, reuse the same password everywhere and put ourselves at risk. With a password manager, you can remove that risk without taking on the heavy mental load. Using a manager means you only have to remember one password (the master password for the manager), and then you can use unique passwords for all your accounts easily. Password managers can also generate new passwords for you to use, ensuring that they are stronger and more unique than "Password1" or "YourNormalPassword+1." The stronger the password is, the longer it will take to crack. If you want to see how long it would take to crack different passwords, check out: Password Monster. Most password managers can also provide a review of your current accounts and passwords. With this, they give you a report of which accounts have been breached, which accounts use the same password as others, and other relevant information to let you know which ones may be at risk and need to be changed. They can also help protect you against phishing scams. Phishing scams are a type of attack where the scammer pretends to be the actual site you want to use. They normally work by sending you emails or texts saying you need to do something on the site (and urgently, for example, an email stating “You just sent a large amount of money to this other place” will make you panic and want to log on to cancel that), and then providing you with a link to a site which looks almost identical to the actual site to get your account details. Password managers can help because it doesn't matter how good the fake site is (and presumably it is good if you've gotten as far as trying to enter your details), the password manager won't auto-populate the details if the URL of the site is wrong. You can also use a password manager to securely share passwords. If you need to give your login details to someone else, rather than sending them the password in a way that could be read by others instead you can use a password manager to create a secure link to share instead. By sharing details this way you can also control other aspects such as how long they can view the password, and whether the link will only work for them or anyone with a copy of the link. Organization Password managers allow you to keep all your passwords organized in one place. This means that you don't have to worry about forgetting where you stored a password or which password you used for a particular account. It’s also great for keeping track of which sites you already have an account for, so you don’t try to sign up to the same site twice. Efficiency A password manager can also save you time by automatically filling in your login details for you. This can be especially helpful if you have multiple accounts to manage or if you switch between devices. Does it mean I can be hacked once, and they get everything? Technically yes, but this is still a safer method than reusing passwords, and a more practical method than having you try to memorise a large number of complex passwords. No password storage method is without risk - reusing has a greater risk of being cracked, and remembering everything has a greater risk of you forgetting them. Password managers are more practical (meaning you're more likely to keep using them because they're not awful to deal with), and also they're more secure than most websites. There are a lot of in-depth articles about how password managers work, but the gist is that they work in such a way that even they don't know your master password, meaning that even they can't get access to your passwords because everything is encrypted. So even if someone does get into their servers and steal your data, they still have to crack your master password first. You can keep everything even more secure by enabling two-factor authentication as well. Then even if they manage to get your master password, they would still be prevented access unless they also had the secondary identification required. What all this means is that yes if they get in they would have access to all your accounts - but they would have a much harder time getting access in the first place. What to look for? Usability Most password managers give a free trial period, so use them to see how comfortable you are with using them. The majority work in the same way (for example with browser extensions), but you may find some make more sense to you than others. It’s worth taking the time to determine how easy it is for you to use at the start, because if some aspect of the process frustrates you then you’re more likely to stop using it and end up back at square one. Test it by seeing how easy it is to add a new password to the manager, how easy it is to use the manager to log into a website of your choice, and also how well it works across all your devices (as most password managers also have an app so you can access it via your phone as well as your desktop). Pricing Most managers only cost a few dollars a month, but it’s still worth doing a comparison to ensure you’re paying an amount that you are comfortable with. Reputation When it comes to security it’s best to think about what happens ‘when’ you get breached, not ‘if’ you will. The same thought applies to password managers. See if they have a history of breaches, and if so how the company responds to them. Being breached previously is not necessarily a deal breaker, but how they respond to it may be. If they are slow to let users know about a breach (so that users can update their passwords) or try to cover it up , then that password manager is probably not the place to trust with your credentials. For example, in late 2022 LastPass had a severe data breach and mishandled it to the point that they lost a lot of peoples’ trust and there were a lot of calls for people to move to different password managers instead. Using a password manager is not only convenient, but it’s also essential for online security. It helps to eliminate the risk of using the same password across multiple accounts and increases the strength of passwords by generating new ones. They allow you to be more organized and efficient by keeping all passwords in one secure location and auto-filling them in when needed. While no method of password storage is completely risk-free, password managers are a practical and secure solution to the problem. That’s why the “technical” people you know want you to use one.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Substance of Stories</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/02/03/Importance-of-Stories.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Substance of Stories" /><published>2023-02-03T21:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-02-03T21:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/02/03/Importance-of-Stories</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/02/03/Importance-of-Stories.html"><![CDATA[Once upon a time, there was a group of people sitting around a campfire. They were trading stories. Stories have been a part of human culture for thousands of years, and for all that time people have been captivated by characters who do not exist, doing daring deeds in places that never were. Stories play an important role in communication, in helping us connect with each other, and in inspiring us. Through stories, we educate and entertain. In this blog post, we will explore the impact of stories on the world.
<p/>
Let us start at the beginning, or as near to it as we can get. The world's oldest known story is believed to be the Sumerian epic poem "The Epic of Gilgamesh," and it dates back to around 2100 BC. The story follows the eponymous hero on their quest for immortality. Spoiler alert for a story over 4000 years old, but the main takeaway from the tale is about the inevitability of death. This means that for over 4000 years (at least), we have been using stories as a form of education, on all sorts of topics. We use this story to teach each other about the futility of searching for immortality. We use the story of Little Red Riding Hood to learn that strangers in the woods perhaps shouldn’t be trusted. We use tales of the Laboon, or the "wave that eats people," to know the warning signs for tsunamis. We use stories to learn about the world.
<p/>
Through stories, we can communicate and inform across generations. The story that I once heard to illustrate this point was about a volcano. One day, a little boy saw the volcano erupt. He witnessed the lava flow and the destruction of the landscape. He survived, grew up, and had a family of his own. The volcano remained dormant all the while. When he was old, he told his grandchildren about the volcano erupting. They didn’t believe him — the mountain had never changed for them, it was just a mountain. They then grew up and had their own families. If they decided one day to say, "You know, my grandfather said once that that mountain there vomited fire out of it," they would all laugh together about how silly an idea that was. Mountains are solid; they don’t spit fire. The future generations were wholly unprepared when the volcano erupted again. However, if it wasn't just a volcano, but the story of a God enraged by the people, it was more likely to be told again. A mountain may "just be a mountain," but everyone knew from their other stories that Gods were emotional and sometimes destructive beings. A tale that included warning signs of the Gods’ anger, such as the ground shaking, is much more interesting. The future generations would remember the old story, recognise the warning signs (which happened to also be the warning signs for the volcano eruption), and be more prepared.
<p/>
Neil Gaiman is one of many people who once said that stories are a way of using lies to tell the truth. It seems fitting then, that I use one of his stories next to talk about stories as inspiration. Through stories, we can do things we have never done before and experience the world in new ways. If we’re reading about how a character similar to us overcomes deadly situations, we also learn that we have the potential to overcome dangerous odds too. In Neil Gaiman’s book Coraline, the main villain is the "Other Mother". Coraline discovers throughout the book just how dangerous and scary the Other Mother can be, which means that when the Other Mother kidnaps her parents, she knows exactly how dangerous her quest to get them back is. In the real world, there is no Other Mother — it’s all a lie. But plenty of readers have used this and other tales of bravery to inspire themselves to handle the problems in their own lives. If Coraline can do it, why can’t they? Whether it’s a story of achieving your dreams or one of surviving your nightmares, reading or hearing stories of others' success shows us that success is possible.
<p/>
Of course, stories don’t only inspire, communicate, and educate. They entertain. This is equally as important as everything else covered so far, as entertainment is important to your mental health. Laughing at a story together with others allows you to form deeper bonds with each other. Stepping into the world of the story lets you forget about your own world and worries for a while. Stories following a group of friends can help with feelings of loneliness and isolation. Stories remove boredom and stimulate the mind. A ‘happily ever after’ can leave you feeling happy and satisfied. 
<p/>
The importance of stories cannot be overstated. From education and communication across generations, to inspiration and entertainment in our day-to-day lives, stories have a huge impact on our lives. Whether they were first told 4000 years ago or today, stories play a vital role in helping us understand ourselves, each other, and the wider world around us, making them an integral part of the human experience.]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Once upon a time, there was a group of people sitting around a campfire. They were trading stories. Stories have been a part of human culture for thousands of years, and for all that time people have been captivated by characters who do not exist, doing daring deeds in places that never were. Stories play an important role in communication, in helping us connect with each other, and in inspiring us. Through stories, we educate and entertain. In this blog post, we will explore the impact of stories on the world. Let us start at the beginning, or as near to it as we can get. The world's oldest known story is believed to be the Sumerian epic poem "The Epic of Gilgamesh," and it dates back to around 2100 BC. The story follows the eponymous hero on their quest for immortality. Spoiler alert for a story over 4000 years old, but the main takeaway from the tale is about the inevitability of death. This means that for over 4000 years (at least), we have been using stories as a form of education, on all sorts of topics. We use this story to teach each other about the futility of searching for immortality. We use the story of Little Red Riding Hood to learn that strangers in the woods perhaps shouldn’t be trusted. We use tales of the Laboon, or the "wave that eats people," to know the warning signs for tsunamis. We use stories to learn about the world. Through stories, we can communicate and inform across generations. The story that I once heard to illustrate this point was about a volcano. One day, a little boy saw the volcano erupt. He witnessed the lava flow and the destruction of the landscape. He survived, grew up, and had a family of his own. The volcano remained dormant all the while. When he was old, he told his grandchildren about the volcano erupting. They didn’t believe him — the mountain had never changed for them, it was just a mountain. They then grew up and had their own families. If they decided one day to say, "You know, my grandfather said once that that mountain there vomited fire out of it," they would all laugh together about how silly an idea that was. Mountains are solid; they don’t spit fire. The future generations were wholly unprepared when the volcano erupted again. However, if it wasn't just a volcano, but the story of a God enraged by the people, it was more likely to be told again. A mountain may "just be a mountain," but everyone knew from their other stories that Gods were emotional and sometimes destructive beings. A tale that included warning signs of the Gods’ anger, such as the ground shaking, is much more interesting. The future generations would remember the old story, recognise the warning signs (which happened to also be the warning signs for the volcano eruption), and be more prepared. Neil Gaiman is one of many people who once said that stories are a way of using lies to tell the truth. It seems fitting then, that I use one of his stories next to talk about stories as inspiration. Through stories, we can do things we have never done before and experience the world in new ways. If we’re reading about how a character similar to us overcomes deadly situations, we also learn that we have the potential to overcome dangerous odds too. In Neil Gaiman’s book Coraline, the main villain is the "Other Mother". Coraline discovers throughout the book just how dangerous and scary the Other Mother can be, which means that when the Other Mother kidnaps her parents, she knows exactly how dangerous her quest to get them back is. In the real world, there is no Other Mother — it’s all a lie. But plenty of readers have used this and other tales of bravery to inspire themselves to handle the problems in their own lives. If Coraline can do it, why can’t they? Whether it’s a story of achieving your dreams or one of surviving your nightmares, reading or hearing stories of others' success shows us that success is possible. Of course, stories don’t only inspire, communicate, and educate. They entertain. This is equally as important as everything else covered so far, as entertainment is important to your mental health. Laughing at a story together with others allows you to form deeper bonds with each other. Stepping into the world of the story lets you forget about your own world and worries for a while. Stories following a group of friends can help with feelings of loneliness and isolation. Stories remove boredom and stimulate the mind. A ‘happily ever after’ can leave you feeling happy and satisfied.  The importance of stories cannot be overstated. From education and communication across generations, to inspiration and entertainment in our day-to-day lives, stories have a huge impact on our lives. Whether they were first told 4000 years ago or today, stories play a vital role in helping us understand ourselves, each other, and the wider world around us, making them an integral part of the human experience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Rise of AI in Content Creation: The Ethical Implications of Using AI to Write Blog Posts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/08/Rise-Of-AI-Content.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rise of AI in Content Creation: The Ethical Implications of Using AI to Write Blog Posts" /><published>2023-01-08T15:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-01-08T15:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/01/08/Rise-Of-AI-Content</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/08/Rise-Of-AI-Content.html"><![CDATA[The following blog post was written entirely by AI, using <a href="https://chat.openai.com/"target="_blank">ChatGPT</a> and the following prompt:
<p/>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
    "Write a blog post about: 
    <ul>
        <li>AI 
        <li>What OpenAI is specifically 
        <li>The fact that this post was written using this prompt 
        <li>and then discuss the ethics of using AI to write a blog post in general."
    </ul>
</blockquote>
<p/>
<i>(The resulting text has not been edited in any way.)</i>
<p/>
<hr>
<p/>
Artificial intelligence (AI) is a rapidly advancing field of technology that has the potential to revolutionize many aspects of our lives, from the way we work and communicate to the way we interact with the world around us. AI systems are capable of learning, adapting, and making decisions based on data and algorithms, and can perform tasks that would be impossible or impractical for humans to do.
<p/>
One of the leading organizations in the field of AI is OpenAI, a nonprofit research institute founded by Elon Musk and other prominent figures in the technology industry. OpenAI is focused on advancing the field of AI through research and development of new algorithms, models, and technologies. The organization's mission is to ensure that AI is developed in a responsible and ethical manner, and that its benefits are widely shared and accessible.
<p/>
OpenAI is involved in a range of projects and initiatives, including development of cutting-edge AI models, collaboration with other organizations and researchers, and public education and outreach. Some of the organization's notable achievements include the development of GPT-3, the largest and most powerful language model to date, and the creation of DALL-E, an AI system that can generate images from text descriptions.
<p/>
This blog post was written using a prompt provided by OpenAI's Assistant language model. Assistant is a large language model trained by OpenAI that can generate human-like text based on a given input. This technology has many potential applications, from generating content for websites and social media to providing personalized assistance and recommendations.
<p/>
However, the use of AI to generate content raises some ethical concerns. Some people argue that using AI to write blog posts and other forms of text is a form of plagiarism, since the AI is essentially copying the work of other writers without attribution. This is a valid concern, and it is important for the creators and users of AI systems to be transparent and accountable for the content they generate.
<p/>
Another ethical concern is that using AI to write blog posts can lead to a lack of originality and creativity. AI systems are based on algorithms and data, and are not capable of the same level of creativity and originality as human writers. This can result in content that is dull and uninteresting, and that lacks the unique perspective and voice of a human writer.
<p/>
Additionally, some people argue that using AI to write blog posts could potentially harm the quality and value of content on the internet. If AI systems are able to generate high-quality content quickly and inexpensively, it could make it more difficult for human writers to compete and earn a living from their work. This could lead to a decline in the overall quality and diversity of content on the internet, and could have negative consequences for the creative and intellectual industries.
<p/>
Overall, the ethics of using AI to write blog posts is a complex and contentious issue. While AI can provide many benefits and opportunities, it is important to consider the potential drawbacks and ethical concerns associated with its use. As AI continues to advance and become more widely used, it will be important to have open and thoughtful discussions about the best ways to harness its power and ensure its responsible and ethical development.
<p/>
One approach to addressing the ethical concerns of using AI to write blog posts is to develop and implement guidelines and best practices for the use of AI in content creation. This could include standards for transparency, accountability, and attribution, as well as strategies for promoting originality and creativity.
<p/>
For example, organizations and individuals using AI to generate content could be required to clearly identify and label AI-generated content, and to provide appropriate attribution to the AI systems and algorithms used. This would help to ensure that the work of AI systems is recognized and valued, and that it is not mistaken for the work of human writers.
<p/>
In addition, organizations and individuals using AI to generate content could be encouraged to develop and use AI systems that are capable of originality and creativity, rather than simply copying and regurgitating existing content. This could be done through the use of advanced AI algorithms and techniques, such as adversarial learning and generative models, that are designed to produce novel and creative outputs.
<p/>
Finally, organizations and individuals using AI to generate content could be encouraged to consider the potential impacts of AI on the creative and intellectual industries, and to take steps to ensure that human writers are not unfairly disadvantaged. This could include initiatives to support and promote human writers, such as providing education, training, and mentorship programs, and creating opportunities for human writers to collaborate with AI systems.
<p/>
By taking these and other steps, we can help to ensure that the use of AI to write blog posts is responsible and ethical, and that it promotes originality, creativity, and diversity in content on the internet.
<p/>
It is also important to note that the use of AI to write blog posts is still in its early stages, and that the technology is likely to evolve and improve over time. As AI systems become more advanced and capable, they may be able to produce even more sophisticated and original content, and may be able to work in collaboration with human writers to produce even better and more engaging blog posts.
<p/>
However, as with any technology, it is important to approach the use of AI to write blog posts with caution and caution. We should be mindful of the potential drawbacks and ethical concerns of using AI in this way, and should take steps to address these concerns in a responsible and thoughtful manner. By doing so, we can help to ensure that the use of AI to write blog posts is a positive and beneficial development for the creative and intellectual industries.
<p/>
In conclusion, the use of AI to write blog posts is a complex and contentious issue that raises a number of ethical concerns. While AI can provide many benefits and opportunities, it is important to consider the potential drawbacks and ethical concerns associated with its use. To address these concerns, organizations and individuals using AI to generate content should develop and implement guidelines and best practices for the use of AI in content creation. By doing so, we can help to ensure that the use of AI to write blog posts is responsible and ethical, and that it promotes the best interests of human writers and the broader creative and intellectual industries.]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following blog post was written entirely by AI, using ChatGPT and the following prompt: "Write a blog post about: AI What OpenAI is specifically The fact that this post was written using this prompt and then discuss the ethics of using AI to write a blog post in general." (The resulting text has not been edited in any way.) Artificial intelligence (AI) is a rapidly advancing field of technology that has the potential to revolutionize many aspects of our lives, from the way we work and communicate to the way we interact with the world around us. AI systems are capable of learning, adapting, and making decisions based on data and algorithms, and can perform tasks that would be impossible or impractical for humans to do. One of the leading organizations in the field of AI is OpenAI, a nonprofit research institute founded by Elon Musk and other prominent figures in the technology industry. OpenAI is focused on advancing the field of AI through research and development of new algorithms, models, and technologies. The organization's mission is to ensure that AI is developed in a responsible and ethical manner, and that its benefits are widely shared and accessible. OpenAI is involved in a range of projects and initiatives, including development of cutting-edge AI models, collaboration with other organizations and researchers, and public education and outreach. Some of the organization's notable achievements include the development of GPT-3, the largest and most powerful language model to date, and the creation of DALL-E, an AI system that can generate images from text descriptions. This blog post was written using a prompt provided by OpenAI's Assistant language model. Assistant is a large language model trained by OpenAI that can generate human-like text based on a given input. This technology has many potential applications, from generating content for websites and social media to providing personalized assistance and recommendations. However, the use of AI to generate content raises some ethical concerns. Some people argue that using AI to write blog posts and other forms of text is a form of plagiarism, since the AI is essentially copying the work of other writers without attribution. This is a valid concern, and it is important for the creators and users of AI systems to be transparent and accountable for the content they generate. Another ethical concern is that using AI to write blog posts can lead to a lack of originality and creativity. AI systems are based on algorithms and data, and are not capable of the same level of creativity and originality as human writers. This can result in content that is dull and uninteresting, and that lacks the unique perspective and voice of a human writer. Additionally, some people argue that using AI to write blog posts could potentially harm the quality and value of content on the internet. If AI systems are able to generate high-quality content quickly and inexpensively, it could make it more difficult for human writers to compete and earn a living from their work. This could lead to a decline in the overall quality and diversity of content on the internet, and could have negative consequences for the creative and intellectual industries. Overall, the ethics of using AI to write blog posts is a complex and contentious issue. While AI can provide many benefits and opportunities, it is important to consider the potential drawbacks and ethical concerns associated with its use. As AI continues to advance and become more widely used, it will be important to have open and thoughtful discussions about the best ways to harness its power and ensure its responsible and ethical development. One approach to addressing the ethical concerns of using AI to write blog posts is to develop and implement guidelines and best practices for the use of AI in content creation. This could include standards for transparency, accountability, and attribution, as well as strategies for promoting originality and creativity. For example, organizations and individuals using AI to generate content could be required to clearly identify and label AI-generated content, and to provide appropriate attribution to the AI systems and algorithms used. This would help to ensure that the work of AI systems is recognized and valued, and that it is not mistaken for the work of human writers. In addition, organizations and individuals using AI to generate content could be encouraged to develop and use AI systems that are capable of originality and creativity, rather than simply copying and regurgitating existing content. This could be done through the use of advanced AI algorithms and techniques, such as adversarial learning and generative models, that are designed to produce novel and creative outputs. Finally, organizations and individuals using AI to generate content could be encouraged to consider the potential impacts of AI on the creative and intellectual industries, and to take steps to ensure that human writers are not unfairly disadvantaged. This could include initiatives to support and promote human writers, such as providing education, training, and mentorship programs, and creating opportunities for human writers to collaborate with AI systems. By taking these and other steps, we can help to ensure that the use of AI to write blog posts is responsible and ethical, and that it promotes originality, creativity, and diversity in content on the internet. It is also important to note that the use of AI to write blog posts is still in its early stages, and that the technology is likely to evolve and improve over time. As AI systems become more advanced and capable, they may be able to produce even more sophisticated and original content, and may be able to work in collaboration with human writers to produce even better and more engaging blog posts. However, as with any technology, it is important to approach the use of AI to write blog posts with caution and caution. We should be mindful of the potential drawbacks and ethical concerns of using AI in this way, and should take steps to address these concerns in a responsible and thoughtful manner. By doing so, we can help to ensure that the use of AI to write blog posts is a positive and beneficial development for the creative and intellectual industries. In conclusion, the use of AI to write blog posts is a complex and contentious issue that raises a number of ethical concerns. While AI can provide many benefits and opportunities, it is important to consider the potential drawbacks and ethical concerns associated with its use. To address these concerns, organizations and individuals using AI to generate content should develop and implement guidelines and best practices for the use of AI in content creation. By doing so, we can help to ensure that the use of AI to write blog posts is responsible and ethical, and that it promotes the best interests of human writers and the broader creative and intellectual industries.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the Future of Software Development at NDC Melbourne</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/12/06/NDC-Review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the Future of Software Development at NDC Melbourne" /><published>2022-12-06T12:58:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-12-06T12:58:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/12/06/NDC-Review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/12/06/NDC-Review.html"><![CDATA[Earlier this year, I went to and spoke at NDC Melbourne. 
<p/>
<h2>What is NDC?</h2>
A technical conference - although it is now a worldwide event, NDC stands for "Norwegian Developers Conference" to highlight its origins.
<p/>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"Since its start-up in Oslo 2008, the Norwegian Developers Conference (NDC) quickly became Europe`s largest conferences for .NET & Agile open space development. However, since then, the conference has come a long way.

NDC conferences are currently running in Oslo (since 2008), London (since 2013) and Sydney (from August 2016). 
[...] Even though the majority of NDC's delegates have a .NET background, NDC are no longer solely focusing on .NET and Agile, but all technologies that are interesting for developers."</blockquote>
<figcaption>— <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/ndc-conferences/"target="_blank">NDC via LinkedIn</a></figcaption>
<p>
It's easy to miss out on hearing about the newest developments in the realm of technology, so tech conferences in general are a wonderful opportunity to learn about them.
I find that it reflects a quote often attributed to William Gibson; "the future is already here, it's just not evenly distributed yet".
<p/>
The entire event was amazing, and thankfully the conference organisers made all of the talks freely accessible online.
The complete playlist of talks is available <a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PL03Lrmd9CiGccT0ERZ9YywROnQryo6gLG"target="_blank">here</a>:
<p align="center">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PL03Lrmd9CiGccT0ERZ9YywROnQryo6gLG" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</p>
<br/>
Richard Campbell's keynote, "The Next Decade of Software Development," was a stand-out presentation covering an overview of all the interesting ways that technology has changed over the last several decades, complete with predictions for the future for the next ten years.
<br/>
<br/>
There was a lot of common sense in this discussion, such the idea that some things will not change any time soon, like the proliferation of cloud computing, mobile technology, and the use of "catastrophic amounts of data."
<br/>
<br/>
Other things however are likely to change, like:
<ul>
    <li>The advancement of silicon chip development possibly slowing down due to reaching limits in the number of transistors that can fit within a space at an atomic level. This could lead to a shift in emphasis away from obtaining more processing power and towards optimising and refining software resource usage, similar to how software development was done when processing power was more limited. As Mark Twain once said, “History never repeats itself, but it does often rhyme.”
    <li>The use of 5G everywhere. He also provided a clear explanation of the distinction between 4G and 5G, which basically boils down to the latter's higher frequency, which enables for more data to be transmitted in each cycle but also reduces its range and weakens its penetrating power. Therefore, 5G has the capacity to carry more data but it also has increased disruption risk.
</ul>
Then there are the pandemic impacts, such as: 
<ul>
    <li>The development of the cloud has advanced significantly as a result of everyone working from home, and as a result, it may become more standardised and controlled as it develops into a utility.
    <li>There were also economic impacts, with recessions likely in many countries. Which is why it's important to know your ROI. You should understand how the business you work for makes money, and how your project relates to that. Because companies will be looking to reduce costs, and that can include reducing headcounts. It's interesting to note that since this talk was given there have been high-profile layoffs at quite a few tech companies (such as <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/11/14/technology/amazon-layoffs.html"target="_blank">Amazon</a>, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/11/09/technology/meta-layoffs-facebook.html"target="_blank">Meta</a>, and <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2022/nov/04/twitter-layoffs-elon-musk-revenue-drop"target="_blank">Twitter</a>).
</ul>
Finally there is the 'future tech' section, or more accurately the 'just really cool' section, covering aspects of AI (such as GitHub Copilot) and the nature of quantum computing and the problems that it can more easily solve. 
<p align="center">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/reL-ke2J03o" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</p>
<p/>
Following that, here are some other stand-out talks I liked: 
<p/>
<h3>Unleash the Power of Visual Studio Code - Aaron Powell</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"VS Code is hot, there's no doubt about it being an utterly amazing editor, but I ask you, are you using it to its full potential? Let's go on a journey together and look to unlock the real power that you can get out of VS Code. Whether it's with shortcuts or extensions, environment standardisation and remote development, collaboration to integrations, there's so many things to uncover that can take you from a user to a pro in no time."</blockquote>
<p align="center">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/I5kx__o4S3k" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</p>


<p/>
<h3>Diamonds are forever, so are URLs - Wing Ho</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"Imagine putting up signage saying “Puppies this way, just around the corner”. You follow that sign. Right as you turn the corner, you’re met with a 404 mole rat instead. A rush of realisation, disappointment, anger, ensures.
URLs are forever. Or so they should be. This is the experience you subject your users to, when links aren’t given the love they need. I’ll show you how you could be thinking about your app/website URLs and routes when you are crafting them, and strategies on how to migrate old URLs rather than leaving your users in disarray."</blockquote>
<p align="center">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XDJ7_UvRjis" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</p>

<p/>
<h3>Interviewing like a Boss - Kris Howard</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"If you've been in the tech industry for any length of time, you've probably been asked to participate in interviewing. Lucky folks will receive some basic training from their employer, but most are expected to just figure it out. It can be time-consuming, nerve-wracking, and tedious. You probably don't enjoy doing it, and that can lead to bad hires and painful experiences. Kris has participated in more than 250 interviews at AWS - as both an interviewer and a hiring manager - and has finally come to embrace the process. She'll provide practical tips you can use to conduct more effective interviews, saving you time and making the whole process a lot more enjoyable."</blockquote>
<p align="center">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IJ8Yb1uMZKA" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</p>

<p/>
<h3>Space in the 2020's - Richard Campbell</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"Are the 2020s the decade where regular people get to go into space? Join Richard Campbell as he assembles all the current developments in space flight to look at what the next few years could offer to a regular person on a once-in-a-lifetime trip. Will there be space hotel in orbit around the Earth? What about a resort on the Moon? Could we go further than that? And, most importantly… how much will it cost? The potential is huge, and the impact on mankind is hard to even imagine - maybe science fiction is coming true?"</blockquote>
<p align="center">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/o6cK-m-2stg" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</p>

<p/>
<h3>Mobile App Accessibility - Allison Ravenhall</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"Boring title, fun session: iOS and Android tech demos!
See how assistive technologies work with mobile apps. Screen readers, external keyboards, extreme text size settings, and speech interfaces.
Good, bad, and unusable experiences across a bunch of apps. Names will be named, some may be shamed. Will yours be in the mix?
Get a glimpse at the different ways people are using your app."</blockquote>
<p align="center">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZR8MHFTEtlc" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</p>

<p/>
<h3>Building a Raspberry Pi Robot Arm with NET 6, Blazor and SignalR - Peter Gallagher</h3>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"In this session we'll run through everything needed to build a Robot Arm with a Raspberry Pi, .NET 6 a Blazor App and SignalR.
We'll begin by seeing how easy it is to install .NET 6.
Then we'll see how we've connected up the various components to our Raspberry Pi.
Next we'll spin up a console application to explore how we can control the GPIO on the Pi.
We'll then examine the code to start moving the connected servos for our Raspberry pi based Robot Arm.
Next we'll look at a simple Blazor and SignalR app to control our robot remotely!
Finally we'll have a look at how we can use an Oculus Quest 2 to interact with our Robot Arm in VR!
This session will appeal to all knowledge levels. A working knowledge of programming will help, but all the code will be shared on GitHub!"</blockquote>
<p align="center">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BfR08xNTL4w" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</p>

<p/>
Finally, here's mine: 
<h3>210 x 297 UX Design for the Physical World - Rebecca Platt</h3>
<p align="center">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CwTFVvSC2N0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">"We know the importance of UX, and there is a lot of information out there about good design principles - when on a digital screen. But what about one of the most prevalent interfaces that we all encounter? Whether it's the contract for your mortgage or bills from suppliers, printed documents are still one of the major ways in which we interact with our users. This talk covers design issues and tips unique to the UX of the physical printed world.
(210 x 297 are the dimensions of an A4 page in mm.)"</blockquote>
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Earlier this year, I went to and spoke at NDC Melbourne. What is NDC? A technical conference - although it is now a worldwide event, NDC stands for "Norwegian Developers Conference" to highlight its origins. "Since its start-up in Oslo 2008, the Norwegian Developers Conference (NDC) quickly became Europe`s largest conferences for .NET & Agile open space development. However, since then, the conference has come a long way.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Letters From My Good Friend Jonathan Harker</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/11/05/Dracula-Daily-Review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letters From My Good Friend Jonathan Harker" /><published>2022-11-05T12:58:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-11-05T12:58:00+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/11/05/Dracula-Daily-Review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/11/05/Dracula-Daily-Review.html"><![CDATA[Prior to this year, I had never read Dracula by Bram Stoker. It was not on my "to read" list, and being notoriously uneasy with horror films I had never given it a second thought.
<p/>
Then I discovered Dracula Daily.
<p/>
<h2>What is Dracula Daily?</h2>
<br/>
<a href="https://draculadaily.substack.com/" target="_blank">Dracula Daily</a> is a newsletter that emails you the entirety of Dracula in a series of emails. As Dracula is an epistolary novel, every part has a date attached to it. The newsletter follows the timeline in the novel by sending out the events that take place on each day of the story.
<p/>
For example, if the characters write about events happening on October 3rd, then you will receive an email about those events on that date.
<p/>
The timeline in Dracula runs from May 3rd until November 7th. By reading the events on the dates that they happen, you get to experience the story in 'real time'. It also means that everyone else also taking part in Dracula Daily is up to the same stage of the story - we're all reading it together as one large book club.
<p/>
That book club aspect of it is what led me to sign up back in May, and it has become a huge part of the enjoyment that I get out of reading it. Sure, I could have read Dracula in a shorter timeframe and enjoyed it - but by sticking to the email format I got (among many things) a sense of community.
<p/>
On any given day that I received a Dracula Daily email, my process was this:
<ol>
    <li>Read the email.
    <li>Check social media (such as Tumblr, Twitter, etc) to see what others have posted about the latest email.
</ol>
<p/>
With so many people reading the same part of the book as I was, there were some lively discussions online between everyone. Every email seemed to result in nuanced breakdowns from others, and perspectives that I would never have considered on my own. But for every post teaching me something new about the 1890s (like did you know the postal service at the time would <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/21/business/21digi.html?adxnnl=1&adxnnlx=1267470299-TxuOOpsKkQg6AhS78K9ptg" target="_blank">deliver to houses multiple times a day</a>? You could send a letter in the morning and expect an answer that afternoon), there were also plenty of memes and fanart and creativity.
<p/>
At the time of writing this post, I am near the end of the book but have not finished it yet. Somehow, even now I still don't know how the story ends. The fact that people are avoiding posting spoilers on a book 125 years old is hilarious, but also much appreciated on my part. Instead, they wait until the emails 'catch up' to that part of the novel, and then publish their tweets and blog posts saying <i>"I've been waiting for this part to happen! Here's everything I waited to say about it."</i> It's a charming piece of consideration and really speaks to the 'community' aspect of it all.
<p/>
<h2>Thoughts on the novel itself</h2>
<br/>
When I started reading I found out very quickly that though I knew what a vampire was and understood the basics of Dracula as a character, I had no idea what happened in the actual story of Dracula. Those of you that are reading this but have not read the novel yet - did you know there's a cowboy in it? He's even a main character!
<p/>
If your knowledge of the story comes from film adaptions, you may be surprised to know that apparently most (if not all) of the adaptions are notorious for not sticking to the source material. Having not watched any of the films I cannot confirm that, but I can instead confirm that nothing I had picked up via cultural osmosis had prepared me for what happens in the book.
<p/>
<h4>The Plot</h4> 
Jonathan Harker, a recently qualified solicitor, journeys from England to Transylvania to Count Dracula's castle. Dracula is planning to move to England, and so Jonathan has been sent there to help with this. Things go rather downhill for Jonathan from there, as he is imprisoned in the castle for several months. Dracula then makes his way to England and starts causing all sorts of problems for the other main characters.
<p/>
Plot summary aside, the status of the book as a classic is well deserved. The group of main characters are all interesting individuals, and while some are eccentric none seem unrealistic. The events that happen are devastating in the best way, and the emotional impacts still resonate when reading over a century after the book was first published.
<p/>
Returning to the 'Dracula Daily' phenomenon; the email format also made the book seem more accessible. I used to read on the train travelling to and from work, but thanks to the ~world events~ of the past few years, I spend a lot more time working from home. Which is great for my commute time, but less great for my "to read" list progress. It is difficult to find time to pick up a book when it is not part of your routine. But reading an email? Sure, I have time for that! Having the book broken up into smaller more manageable chunks completely got me through the mental hurdle of finding time to read.
<p/>
I also really enjoy the fact that it has popularised reading the classics, as others wanted to recreate or extend the "Dracula Daily" experience - but since the format involves sharing the novel, everyone has been using books that are already public domain. I have already started another book thanks to this: <a href="https://carmillaweekly.substack.com" target="_blank">Carmilla by Sheridan Le Fanu</a> - which I am about halfway through.
<p/>
These are the books I signed up for that haven't started yet:
<ul>
    <li><a href="https://frankweekly.substack.com" target="_blank">Frankenstein by  Mary Shelley</a> - Starting Feb 1, 2023
    <li><a href="https://lesmisletters.substack.com" target="_blank">Les Misérables by Victor Hugo</a> - Starting Jan 1, 2023
    <li><a href="https://gatsbyweekly.substack.com" target="_blank">The Great Gatsby by F. Scott Fitzgerald</a> - Starting 'soon'
    <li><a href="https://whaleweekly.substack.com" target="_blank">Moby Dick by Herman Melville</a> - Starting Nov 21, 2022
</ul>
<p/>
...And here are other mailing lists of books that I've heard of but didn't sign up for (because I realised I may have overdone things already):
<ul>
    <li><a href="https://carmillaquarterly.substack.com/" target="_blank">Carmilla by Sheridan Le Fanu</a> - Like Carmilla Weekly that I linked previously, but instead the book is spread over four longer emails.
    <li><a href="https://poefortnightly.substack.com/" target="_blank">Various works of Edgar Allan Poe</a> - Updated fortnightly
    <li><a href="https://thewomaninwhiteweekly.substack.com/" target="_blank">The Woman In White by Wilkie Collins</a> - Updated weekly
    <li><a href="https://prideandprejudiceweekly.substack.com/" target="_blank">Pride and Prejudice by Jane Austen</a> - Starting Mar 10, 2023
    <li><a href="https://nightlyknights.substack.com/" target="_blank">Nightly Knights</a> - A collection of Arthurian tales.
    <li><a href="https://romeoandjulietregular.substack.com/" target="_blank">Romeo and Juliet by William Shakespeare</a>
    <li><a href="https://epistulae.substack.com/" target="_blank">Letters of Cicero as translated by E. S. Shuckburgh</a>
    <li><a href="https://lettersfromwatson.substack.com/" target="_blank">Sherlock Holmes Short Stories</a> - Starting Jan 1, 2023
    <li><a href="https://divinacommedia.substack.com/" target="_blank">The Divine Comedy by Dante Alighieri</a> - Starting Apr 7, 2023
    <li><a href="https://dangerousliaisonsdaily.substack.com/" target="_blank">Dangerous Liaisons by Pierre Choderlos de Laclos</a>
</ul>
It was a pleasure to be a part of Dracula Daily, and I'm looking forward to participating in these upcoming 'book clubs' in the future. Come join me!
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Prior to this year, I had never read Dracula by Bram Stoker. It was not on my "to read" list, and being notoriously uneasy with horror films I had never given it a second thought. Then I discovered Dracula Daily. What is Dracula Daily? Dracula Daily is a newsletter that emails you the entirety of Dracula in a series of emails. As Dracula is an epistolary novel, every part has a date attached to it. The newsletter follows the timeline in the novel by sending out the events that take place on each day of the story. For example, if the characters write about events happening on October 3rd, then you will receive an email about those events on that date. The timeline in Dracula runs from May 3rd until November 7th. By reading the events on the dates that they happen, you get to experience the story in 'real time'. It also means that everyone else also taking part in Dracula Daily is up to the same stage of the story - we're all reading it together as one large book club. That book club aspect of it is what led me to sign up back in May, and it has become a huge part of the enjoyment that I get out of reading it. Sure, I could have read Dracula in a shorter timeframe and enjoyed it - but by sticking to the email format I got (among many things) a sense of community. On any given day that I received a Dracula Daily email, my process was this: Read the email. Check social media (such as Tumblr, Twitter, etc) to see what others have posted about the latest email. With so many people reading the same part of the book as I was, there were some lively discussions online between everyone. Every email seemed to result in nuanced breakdowns from others, and perspectives that I would never have considered on my own. But for every post teaching me something new about the 1890s (like did you know the postal service at the time would deliver to houses multiple times a day? You could send a letter in the morning and expect an answer that afternoon), there were also plenty of memes and fanart and creativity. At the time of writing this post, I am near the end of the book but have not finished it yet. Somehow, even now I still don't know how the story ends. The fact that people are avoiding posting spoilers on a book 125 years old is hilarious, but also much appreciated on my part. Instead, they wait until the emails 'catch up' to that part of the novel, and then publish their tweets and blog posts saying "I've been waiting for this part to happen! Here's everything I waited to say about it." It's a charming piece of consideration and really speaks to the 'community' aspect of it all. Thoughts on the novel itself When I started reading I found out very quickly that though I knew what a vampire was and understood the basics of Dracula as a character, I had no idea what happened in the actual story of Dracula. Those of you that are reading this but have not read the novel yet - did you know there's a cowboy in it? He's even a main character! If your knowledge of the story comes from film adaptions, you may be surprised to know that apparently most (if not all) of the adaptions are notorious for not sticking to the source material. Having not watched any of the films I cannot confirm that, but I can instead confirm that nothing I had picked up via cultural osmosis had prepared me for what happens in the book. The Plot Jonathan Harker, a recently qualified solicitor, journeys from England to Transylvania to Count Dracula's castle. Dracula is planning to move to England, and so Jonathan has been sent there to help with this. Things go rather downhill for Jonathan from there, as he is imprisoned in the castle for several months. Dracula then makes his way to England and starts causing all sorts of problems for the other main characters. Plot summary aside, the status of the book as a classic is well deserved. The group of main characters are all interesting individuals, and while some are eccentric none seem unrealistic. The events that happen are devastating in the best way, and the emotional impacts still resonate when reading over a century after the book was first published. Returning to the 'Dracula Daily' phenomenon; the email format also made the book seem more accessible. I used to read on the train travelling to and from work, but thanks to the ~world events~ of the past few years, I spend a lot more time working from home. Which is great for my commute time, but less great for my "to read" list progress. It is difficult to find time to pick up a book when it is not part of your routine. But reading an email? Sure, I have time for that! Having the book broken up into smaller more manageable chunks completely got me through the mental hurdle of finding time to read. I also really enjoy the fact that it has popularised reading the classics, as others wanted to recreate or extend the "Dracula Daily" experience - but since the format involves sharing the novel, everyone has been using books that are already public domain. I have already started another book thanks to this: Carmilla by Sheridan Le Fanu - which I am about halfway through. These are the books I signed up for that haven't started yet: Frankenstein by Mary Shelley - Starting Feb 1, 2023 Les Misérables by Victor Hugo - Starting Jan 1, 2023 The Great Gatsby by F. Scott Fitzgerald - Starting 'soon' Moby Dick by Herman Melville - Starting Nov 21, 2022 ...And here are other mailing lists of books that I've heard of but didn't sign up for (because I realised I may have overdone things already): Carmilla by Sheridan Le Fanu - Like Carmilla Weekly that I linked previously, but instead the book is spread over four longer emails. Various works of Edgar Allan Poe - Updated fortnightly The Woman In White by Wilkie Collins - Updated weekly Pride and Prejudice by Jane Austen - Starting Mar 10, 2023 Nightly Knights - A collection of Arthurian tales. Romeo and Juliet by William Shakespeare Letters of Cicero as translated by E. S. Shuckburgh Sherlock Holmes Short Stories - Starting Jan 1, 2023 The Divine Comedy by Dante Alighieri - Starting Apr 7, 2023 Dangerous Liaisons by Pierre Choderlos de Laclos It was a pleasure to be a part of Dracula Daily, and I'm looking forward to participating in these upcoming 'book clubs' in the future. Come join me!]]></summary></entry></feed>