<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-25T22:32:28+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Rebecca Platt</title><subtitle>Writing Stories and Code</subtitle><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><entry><title type="html">Another AI Model Update: A Review of Gemini 2.5</title><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/04/25/ReviewGemini2.5.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Another AI Model Update: A Review of Gemini 2.5" /><published>2025-04-25T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2025-04-25T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/04/25/ReviewGemini2.5</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/04/25/ReviewGemini2.5.html"><![CDATA[It seems like every time you turn around, there's a new AI technology. Last month there were several, but the one I want to highlight today is <a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/gemini-model-thinking-updates-march-2025/" target="_blank">Gemini 2.5 by Google</a>. It was released the same day as the <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-4o-image-generation/" target="_blank">image generation feature in OpenAI's GPT‑4o</a>, which of course meant that Gemini's arrival was overshadowed by the internet's newfound love of recreating everything in the Studio Ghibli art style.
<p/>

<img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6b129ac5-b0ba-4483-9b0d-7b2e82d35c4d_2016x2016.jpeg" alt="Studio Ghibli style portrait of Rebecca Platt" width="60%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">
<blockquote class="blockquote"style="text-align: center;">Results may vary.</blockquote>

<p/>
Even so, I heard Gemini was quite good so I thought I'd give it a whirl.
<p/>
My benchmark for testing the coding capabilities of any AI is to see how well it can build a dress-up game, assuming assets are provided.
Attempts with the first publicly available ChatGPT and other early Large Language Models (LLMs) didn't go so well. The request sounds simple initially, but as you start determining the steps required to make such a game the hidden complexities begin to reveal themselves. The early LLMs would certainly try but were not able to provide code that functioned to a sufficient standard for the request.
<p/>
Gemini 2.5 however, had no problems talking me through the steps of my request. This included even letting it propose which language and frameworks to use based on suitability.
<p/>
Gemini is a 'thinking' model, which roughly translated means it can review its reasoning and alter its approach based on this. I like that you can see its thought process, and why it outputs what it does.
As the instructions I gave were fairly vague, it asked clarifying questions to determine the most appropriate design and then got started.
<p/>
The code it generated did still have some errors. That said, when given the error message it was able to both explain the issue and provide a decent solution. The fixes worked well most of the time, and after a fairly short period of time we had a working dress up game proof of concept. So while it wasn't a flawless process, the game was set up much faster than my previous attempts to build it manually.
<p/>
Now, despite working in tech for so long I had never done any Python scripting before, so I thought for my second experiment it would be a good test to see if Gemini could still deliver even when the user was less familiar with the subject. I asked it to create a fairly complex record data migration script. It handled most of the requests for this well too, however it did sometimes ‘forget’ about previous requirements sent, as it would adjust the code as required for the latest request but occasionally it would do so in a way that impacted a previously requested feature.
<p/>
It handled the data migration script so well that I gave it an extra challenge - migrating poorly structured data from a PDF. Amazingly, it handled that task excellently - I was rather impressed.
<p/>
It would be remiss of me to not include a caveat here, that while the technology is improving rapidly it is still not currently at a point where you can forgo understanding the produced code and just leave everything up to AI. For personal projects like I described above AI is hugely beneficial in the initial phases of design and implementation, but its limitations of context mean that it is less effective during feature refinement and general maintenance and debugging, aka a huge part of development.
<p/>
For me, this was evident during the development process as I found that it kept forgetting session history. When I returned the following day to continue I had to get Gemini back up to speed with the current status before we could continue.
<p/>
Gemini is not actually the LLM most praised for its coding abilities - which at the time of writing appears to be Claude 3.7. When compared with other AI models in bench tests, it excelled across multiple areas.
<p/>


<img src="https://www.anthropic.com/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww-cdn.anthropic.com%2Fimages%2F4zrzovbb%2Fwebsite%2F654cf6680d32858dfba9af644f8c4a5b04425af1-2600x2360.png&w=3840&q=75" alt="Benchmark table comparing frontier reasoning models, showing Claude 3.7 with the highest results" width="100%">
<blockquote class="blockquote"style="text-align: center;">Source: <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-3-7-sonnet" target="_blank">Anthropic</a></blockquote>

<p/>
Despite this, the fact that an AI that's considered 'average' for coding output could still produce what I requested to such a high quality is brilliant. If you are starting a personal project and want to use AI for brainstorming and initial development, it's well worth giving Gemini a go.
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It seems like every time you turn around, there's a new AI technology. Last month there were several, but the one I want to highlight today is Gemini 2.5 by Google. It was released the same day as the image generation feature in OpenAI's GPT‑4o, which of course meant that Gemini's arrival was overshadowed by the internet's newfound love of recreating everything in the Studio Ghibli art style.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Algorithm Showed You This Post</title><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/03/27/AnAlgorithmShowedYouThis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Algorithm Showed You This Post" /><published>2025-03-27T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2025-03-27T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/03/27/AnAlgorithmShowedYouThis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/03/27/AnAlgorithmShowedYouThis.html"><![CDATA[I’m feeling some kind of way about the fact that everything we interact with online is driven by algorithms. By that, I mean that the music we listen to is recommended via playlists, the videos we watch appear served up on YouTube’s homepage, the memes and jokes we see are the ones that appear in our various newsfeeds and “for you” pages. Every time we’re just ‘browsing’, we’re being handed content that has been chosen by an external entity - and it's usually chosen to best catch our attention so we can keep looking at our feeds (and ads) for as long as possible.
<p/>
I’m wondering how much I’m missing out on the internet, simply because some algorithms determined that I might prefer other content instead. I’m thinking of the millions and millions of songs that have <a href="https://english.elpais.com/economy-and-business/2024-03-11/music-streaming-giants-eliminate-songs-with-low-play-counts.html" target="_blank">never been listened to by anyone on Spotify</a>. There has to be some fantastic music in there, but it’s unlikely to ever be served up to me or anyone else.
<p/>
<i>"But Rebecca, you don’t have to rely on what is presented to you; use the search bar!"</i> I hear you say. Which is all well and good if I’m searching for something in particular, and if that philosopher’s stone of content appears at the top of the search results. We have been conditioned to <a href="https://www.fireandspark.com/seo-faqs/how-many-people-only-look-at-the-first-page-of-google-results/" target="_blank">only look at the top few results of any search</a>, God forbid we ever look at page two of Google. (If Google even paginates its results anymore - as I wasn’t sure I just checked, and yes it turns out it does still.)
<p/>
I don’t like how it feels to know that the content I’m consuming (and mildly enjoying) has been chosen by something with an agenda other than my enjoyment. Whether that goal is to sell me a product, or make me a product, or to influence my views of the world, or to keep me distracted and numb. It doesn’t really matter what the goal is, only that it most likely has not been made with my best interest in mind.
<p/>
Now, I’m not saying it's time to revoke all social media and reject basic search functionality. Algorithms are probably what led you to reading this after all. It’s difficult to remove something from your life when there’s billions of dollars being spent to make it as addictive as possible.
<p/>
At this point though it's fair to ask: why don't I have this feeling with other forms of media? You could object that people only make the larger budget art (think shows and movies) because they are investing to get a financial return.
<p/>
But there’s a difference between a movie studio saying “hey another superhero film is exactly what our wallets need” and a social media algorithm saying… well, not much actually, as they’re not involved with making anything content-wise. Maybe that’s the issue. With movie studios, at least the creators are being paid, albeit probably poorly, and with profits mostly going to investors. But online, the creators are paid so much less - if they’re even paid at all. We’ve been conditioned to create something and post it online only if we think it will get enough views - if the algorithm determines that it’s an acceptable tool it can use to get someone else to keep looking at somewhat unrelated ads. The film studio asking for Iron Man 15 still has to put some personal investment in. The social media algorithm, however, is working with such small scales that there’s no risk in an individual scenario, and it’s working with an unfathomable number of instances simultaneously.
<p/>
Maybe I would feel better about things if the tech giants put more investment into the content being given to them for free. Would I feel better knowing that Facebook invested financially in a particular posts' creation, or that YouTube footed the costs for another slow motion video of a balloon full of water being burst? Who knows. What I do know now though, is that the current online landscape seems quite dystopian and exploitative, and I don’t have an answer for how to resolve it. Anyway, like and subscribe.
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m feeling some kind of way about the fact that everything we interact with online is driven by algorithms. By that, I mean that the music we listen to is recommended via playlists, the videos we watch appear served up on YouTube’s homepage, the memes and jokes we see are the ones that appear in our various newsfeeds and “for you” pages. Every time we’re just ‘browsing’, we’re being handed content that has been chosen by an external entity - and it's usually chosen to best catch our attention so we can keep looking at our feeds (and ads) for as long as possible. I’m wondering how much I’m missing out on the internet, simply because some algorithms determined that I might prefer other content instead. I’m thinking of the millions and millions of songs that have never been listened to by anyone on Spotify. There has to be some fantastic music in there, but it’s unlikely to ever be served up to me or anyone else. "But Rebecca, you don’t have to rely on what is presented to you; use the search bar!" I hear you say. Which is all well and good if I’m searching for something in particular, and if that philosopher’s stone of content appears at the top of the search results. We have been conditioned to only look at the top few results of any search, God forbid we ever look at page two of Google. (If Google even paginates its results anymore - as I wasn’t sure I just checked, and yes it turns out it does still.) I don’t like how it feels to know that the content I’m consuming (and mildly enjoying) has been chosen by something with an agenda other than my enjoyment. Whether that goal is to sell me a product, or make me a product, or to influence my views of the world, or to keep me distracted and numb. It doesn’t really matter what the goal is, only that it most likely has not been made with my best interest in mind. Now, I’m not saying it's time to revoke all social media and reject basic search functionality. Algorithms are probably what led you to reading this after all. It’s difficult to remove something from your life when there’s billions of dollars being spent to make it as addictive as possible. At this point though it's fair to ask: why don't I have this feeling with other forms of media? You could object that people only make the larger budget art (think shows and movies) because they are investing to get a financial return. But there’s a difference between a movie studio saying “hey another superhero film is exactly what our wallets need” and a social media algorithm saying… well, not much actually, as they’re not involved with making anything content-wise. Maybe that’s the issue. With movie studios, at least the creators are being paid, albeit probably poorly, and with profits mostly going to investors. But online, the creators are paid so much less - if they’re even paid at all. We’ve been conditioned to create something and post it online only if we think it will get enough views - if the algorithm determines that it’s an acceptable tool it can use to get someone else to keep looking at somewhat unrelated ads. The film studio asking for Iron Man 15 still has to put some personal investment in. The social media algorithm, however, is working with such small scales that there’s no risk in an individual scenario, and it’s working with an unfathomable number of instances simultaneously. Maybe I would feel better about things if the tech giants put more investment into the content being given to them for free. Would I feel better knowing that Facebook invested financially in a particular posts' creation, or that YouTube footed the costs for another slow motion video of a balloon full of water being burst? Who knows. What I do know now though, is that the current online landscape seems quite dystopian and exploitative, and I don’t have an answer for how to resolve it. Anyway, like and subscribe.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Remember This: Review of Make It Stick</title><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/02/15/ReviewMakeItStick.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remember This: Review of Make It Stick" /><published>2025-02-15T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2025-02-15T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/02/15/ReviewMakeItStick</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/02/15/ReviewMakeItStick.html"><![CDATA[Sometimes, we face a new challenge and need to learn a lot of information fast. I recently changed roles to a different team at work, which meant working with a completely different set of technologies and pursuing different goals. With so much to learn, I decided it would be better to read up on how to learn effectively, rather than just winging it like I did  during university. Which is why I read <a href="https://www.google.com.au/books/edition/Make_It_Stick/oneWAwAAQBAJ?hl=en" target="_blank"><i>Make It Stick: The Science of Successful Learning</i> by Peter C. Brown, Henry L. Roediger, and Mark A. McDaniel</a>, where the authors review numerous studies on learning methods. It has great advice - and plenty of references to support it all - so it would be remiss of me not to encourage you to read it too.
<p/>
The book’s main recommendations for effective learning are to incorporate these strategies into your revision methods:
<p/>
<h4>Retrieval Practice</h4>
Actively test how well you can retrieve the knowledge from your memory by challenging yourself. This can be done by using flash cards or by quizzing yourself on a regular basis. Interleaving subjects (switching between topics rather than focusing on just one at a time) has also been shown to improve retrieval ability.
<p/>
<h4>Generation</h4>
This technique involves struggling with a problem and trying to generate an answer before reading the solution. Studies referenced in the book show that expending this mental effort increases the retention of the answer once it is revealed.
<p/>
<h4>Elaboration</h4>
Teach others about the subject is a great way to solidify your understanding. As Albert Einstein is often credited with saying, “If you can't explain it simply, you don't understand it well enough.” Organising your thoughts and explaining them to others ensures you have a thorough understanding of the subject. This can either be done by teaching in person or by writing your thoughts out, like in a blog post (#meta).
<p/>
<h4>Contextualisation</h4>
Relating new information to what you already know helps embed it more deeply in your understanding of the world. This understanding of context is more effective than simply knowing about it as an isolated concept.
<p/>
<h4>Reflection</h4>
Taking time to review what you have recently learned, whether by reading, quizzing, or any of the other activities mentioned above, will lead to greater overall retention. Mental rehearsal, or ‘going through the steps in your mind’, is also an effective form of reflection, especially if you are actively analysing the rehearsal subject.
<p/>
One aspect that I like with this book is that it’s evident that the authors took the results from the research into consideration when planning the structure of it. For example, rather than having a chapter dedicated solely to retrieval practice, they interleave all of the recommendations throughout the book. This means that when you read it you experience the benefits of interleaved practice and exposure with the content and see first-hand how effective the learning strategies are.
<p/>
Since reading the book I have been incorporating these techniques into my own study (as mentioned <a href="https://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/01/29/FlashcardExcel.html" target="_blank">here</a>), and personally, I find them to be very effective. Learning new information can be quite daunting, but these study tools make the process much more manageable and effective, regardless of the subject. If you are facing a similar challenge, I highly recommend giving these strategies a try.
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes, we face a new challenge and need to learn a lot of information fast. I recently changed roles to a different team at work, which meant working with a completely different set of technologies and pursuing different goals. With so much to learn, I decided it would be better to read up on how to learn effectively, rather than just winging it like I did during university. Which is why I read Make It Stick: The Science of Successful Learning by Peter C. Brown, Henry L. Roediger, and Mark A. McDaniel, where the authors review numerous studies on learning methods. It has great advice - and plenty of references to support it all - so it would be remiss of me not to encourage you to read it too. The book’s main recommendations for effective learning are to incorporate these strategies into your revision methods: Retrieval Practice Actively test how well you can retrieve the knowledge from your memory by challenging yourself. This can be done by using flash cards or by quizzing yourself on a regular basis. Interleaving subjects (switching between topics rather than focusing on just one at a time) has also been shown to improve retrieval ability. Generation This technique involves struggling with a problem and trying to generate an answer before reading the solution. Studies referenced in the book show that expending this mental effort increases the retention of the answer once it is revealed. Elaboration Teach others about the subject is a great way to solidify your understanding. As Albert Einstein is often credited with saying, “If you can't explain it simply, you don't understand it well enough.” Organising your thoughts and explaining them to others ensures you have a thorough understanding of the subject. This can either be done by teaching in person or by writing your thoughts out, like in a blog post (#meta). Contextualisation Relating new information to what you already know helps embed it more deeply in your understanding of the world. This understanding of context is more effective than simply knowing about it as an isolated concept. Reflection Taking time to review what you have recently learned, whether by reading, quizzing, or any of the other activities mentioned above, will lead to greater overall retention. Mental rehearsal, or ‘going through the steps in your mind’, is also an effective form of reflection, especially if you are actively analysing the rehearsal subject. One aspect that I like with this book is that it’s evident that the authors took the results from the research into consideration when planning the structure of it. For example, rather than having a chapter dedicated solely to retrieval practice, they interleave all of the recommendations throughout the book. This means that when you read it you experience the benefits of interleaved practice and exposure with the content and see first-hand how effective the learning strategies are. Since reading the book I have been incorporating these techniques into my own study (as mentioned here), and personally, I find them to be very effective. Learning new information can be quite daunting, but these study tools make the process much more manageable and effective, regardless of the subject. If you are facing a similar challenge, I highly recommend giving these strategies a try.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Flash Cards in Excel</title><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/01/29/FlashcardExcel.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Flash Cards in Excel" /><published>2025-01-29T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2025-01-29T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/01/29/FlashcardExcel</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2025/01/29/FlashcardExcel.html"><![CDATA[Learning about a whole new topic can be hard. Even when it’s a topic that’s building on foundational knowledge you already know, it can be difficult depending on which learning techniques you use. I wanted to have a better understanding of <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc6749" target="_blank">OAuth</a>. Since reading <a href="https://www.google.com.au/books/edition/_/oneWAwAAQBAJ?hl=en" target="_blank">Make It Stick by Henry L. Roediger III, Mark A. McDaniel, and Peter C. Brown</a>, I knew that one effective way to embed learning was by practicing information retrieval, I decided to make myself (virtual) flash cards to test with.
<p></p>
Now, I could have used an existing app such as <a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/" target="_blank">Anki</a>, but as I was procrastinating as much as possible, I decided to build my own flash card generator using Microsoft Excel.
<p></p>
I figure others might like access to it as well for their own flash cards, so I've put a template version of it on <a href="https://github.com/rapplatt/FlashcardsExcel" target="_blank">GitHub</a>.
<p></p>
<h2>How it works</h2>
The main data is located over five columns: Questions, Answers, Weight, Random, and Result.
<p></p>
<b>Questions</b> are the 'front' of the flashcard, and what will initially be shown to the user.
<p></p>
<b>Answers</b> are the 'back' of the card. Just because the columns are named this way does not mean that you have to structure your flashcards in a question and answer format.
<p></p>
<b>Weight</b> refers to the weighting of each card. Initially they all start at zero, and then the value is increased or decreased when you use the card, depending on whether you answered correctly or not.
<p></p>
<b>Random</b> is a random value between 0 and 1, e.g. 0.3659.
<p></p>
<b>Result</b> is Weight plus Random, as this creates a randomised order for the cards with a slight weighting towards cards that have been answered incorrectly. The lowest value in the Result column is selected first, so through this weighting system incorrectly answered cards will appear more frequently. (And vice versa, correctly answered cards appear less often.)
<p></p>
On the second sheet is a button, which contains the link to the macros that support the flashcard functionality.
<p></p>
Macros are Excel's way of automating actions, and so they can be used to run basic commands.
<p></p>
Click the button, and a new window opens, with the question part of a flashcard displayed. Read the question and once you have thought of an answer, select reveal to see what the answer is. If you were correct then select yes, otherwise select no. At this point the numbers are randomised again and a new card is the new lowest value, and the cycle begins again. Over time you will be able to see on the first sheet which flash cards you consistently struggle with, and you can use that to know what you need to focus on.
<p></p>
There's a few additional features that could be added here, but that's probably enough procrastinating for me for now. I have found that using the cards has been rather useful for building out my understanding of OAuth. That said, you do actually have to revise with the cards in order for it to work, so it's time to get back to learning. If you <a href="https://github.com/rapplatt/FlashcardsExcel" target="_blank">download the the flash cards excel</a> let me know if it helps you - I'd love to know what topics you're using it for!
<p></p>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learning about a whole new topic can be hard. Even when it’s a topic that’s building on foundational knowledge you already know, it can be difficult depending on which learning techniques you use. I wanted to have a better understanding of OAuth. Since reading Make It Stick by Henry L. Roediger III, Mark A. McDaniel, and Peter C. Brown, I knew that one effective way to embed learning was by practicing information retrieval, I decided to make myself (virtual) flash cards to test with. Now, I could have used an existing app such as Anki, but as I was procrastinating as much as possible, I decided to build my own flash card generator using Microsoft Excel. I figure others might like access to it as well for their own flash cards, so I've put a template version of it on GitHub. How it works The main data is located over five columns: Questions, Answers, Weight, Random, and Result. Questions are the 'front' of the flashcard, and what will initially be shown to the user. Answers are the 'back' of the card. Just because the columns are named this way does not mean that you have to structure your flashcards in a question and answer format. Weight refers to the weighting of each card. Initially they all start at zero, and then the value is increased or decreased when you use the card, depending on whether you answered correctly or not. Random is a random value between 0 and 1, e.g. 0.3659. Result is Weight plus Random, as this creates a randomised order for the cards with a slight weighting towards cards that have been answered incorrectly. The lowest value in the Result column is selected first, so through this weighting system incorrectly answered cards will appear more frequently. (And vice versa, correctly answered cards appear less often.) On the second sheet is a button, which contains the link to the macros that support the flashcard functionality. Macros are Excel's way of automating actions, and so they can be used to run basic commands. Click the button, and a new window opens, with the question part of a flashcard displayed. Read the question and once you have thought of an answer, select reveal to see what the answer is. If you were correct then select yes, otherwise select no. At this point the numbers are randomised again and a new card is the new lowest value, and the cycle begins again. Over time you will be able to see on the first sheet which flash cards you consistently struggle with, and you can use that to know what you need to focus on. There's a few additional features that could be added here, but that's probably enough procrastinating for me for now. I have found that using the cards has been rather useful for building out my understanding of OAuth. That said, you do actually have to revise with the cards in order for it to work, so it's time to get back to learning. If you download the the flash cards excel let me know if it helps you - I'd love to know what topics you're using it for!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GraphQL: I Don’t Know What It Is And Now I’m Too Afraid To Ask</title><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/11/06/GraphQL-Refresher.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GraphQL: I Don’t Know What It Is And Now I’m Too Afraid To Ask" /><published>2024-11-06T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-11-06T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/11/06/GraphQL-Refresher</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/11/06/GraphQL-Refresher.html"><![CDATA[<em>The following notes are designed to complement my presentation on GraphQL. Link to the talk will be provided when available. </em></p>
<hr>
<p>
<strong>Until recently, I only had a vague understanding of what GraphQL was.</strong> For those that still aren’t sure, please know that it’s ok not to know. There are so many buzzwords and new technologies being created all the time, it would be impossible to keep up with absolutely everything. In fact, it happens so often that IBM even created a chart to document the process that happens each time - this is the hype cycle of emerging technologies:</p>
<img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2b6cae05-c407-4436-9c6c-cfa7831b98fc_983x294.png" alt="Graph depicting the Hype Cycle" style="width:100%">
<p>This chart goes through five phases:</p>
<ul>
    <li>The <strong>Innovation Trigger</strong>, where the technology is made available to the public for the first time,</li>
    <li>The <strong>Peak of Inflated Expectations</strong> occurs shortly after, as everyone attempts to apply the technology to resolve every scenario ever,</li>
    <li>The <strong>Trough of Disillusionment</strong> is when people realise that the technology did not in fact fix everything,</li>
    <li>The <strong>Slope of Enlightenment</strong> happens as people start using the technology again, but this time with more realistic expectations, and</li>
    <li>The <strong>Plateau of Productivity</strong> occurs when the technology has found it’s place in the technological landscape and is used in appropriate scenarios.</li>
</ul>
<p>Currently, I think GraphQL is coming out of the Slope of Enlightenment and starting to head into the Plateau of Productivity, which also means it’s worth doing a refresher for those of us that missed it the first time around.</p>
<h1 class="header-anchor-post">Why GraphQL Was Created</h1>
<p><strong>Back in the distant past of 2012, Facebook was having some issues with its app.</strong><span> At the time it was essentially an adaptation of the website, and compared to other natively built apps it simply wasn’t working as well - so they decided it was time to rewrite it.</span></p>
<p>Originally they intended to use the existing APIs that they had at the time, which like the majority of the industry were mostly REST APIs.</p>
<h2 class="header-anchor-post">REST Strengths</h2><br/>
<ul>
    <li>Great when working with simple and less volatile data.</li>
    <li>Has individual endpoints that correspond with its available resources, meaning there’s a nice inbuilt separation of concerns already.</li>
    <li>Having stateless operations means that each request is self-contained, which improves scalability and simplifies the underlying back-end architecture.</li>
    <li>Interfaces well with older systems and technologies, which is great when you’re working with legacy systems.</li>
</ul>
<p/>
<h2 class="header-anchor-post">REST Weaknesses</h2>
<p>REST is less effective when working with complex data, such as was required by Facebook to populate the newsfeed. To do so could involve a number of separate REST calls; to get the user’s list of friends, to get the recent statuses made by each of those friends, to get the comments for each of the statuses, to get the likes of the comments of the statuses of the friends…</p>
<ul>
    <li>Doing so would result in an <strong>over-fetching</strong> risk as additional unnecessary data would be retrieved unnecessarily,</li>
    <li>Yet it also suffered from <strong>under-fetching</strong> as all the multiple calls would be required each time the newsfeed is loaded.</li>
    <li>All that additional traffic adds up, and would be especially noticeable on the phones popular back in 2012, which usually only had 1GB RAM.</li>
    <li>Also, all those endpoints from before? Well, any new requirements result in additional endpoints being created, and all the existing ones have ongoing maintenance, including versioning and deprecation.</li>
</ul>
<p/>
<p/>
<h2 class="header-anchor-post">How GraphQL Resolves This</h2>
<p>Instead of traditional approaches, GraphQL works by modelling data as a graph, where data types (like users, posts, comments) are nodes, and the relationships between them (like users posting comments) are the edges connecting those nodes. In this structure, you can traverse between related types, much like how you can move across nodes in a graph.</p>
<div class="captioned-image-container">
    <img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F61e68307-f7ab-42ee-a491-e40ca0057470_653x634.png" alt="Graph of nodes and edges" style="width:100%">
</div>
<p/>
<ul>
    <li>Instead of endpoints, with GraphQL it was now possible to use queries (similar to SQL) to specify exactly what data was required for each use case. This nicely solves both the over-fetching and under-fetching issues.</li>
    <li>This increased data efficiency also means it’s more practical for providing real-time data updates.</li>
    <li>You didn't even have to keep building out endpoints for scenarios. For anything with evolving requirements, it became easy to add in fields without breaking previous versions of the query endpoint.</li>
    <li>GraphQL can also return partial data along with error details, which can be useful when diagnosing issues.</li>
</ul>
<p>This does not mean that GraphQL is perfect for every scenario - there’s a reason why REST APIs are still more common, as shown in the <a href="https://voyager.postman.com/pdf/2023-state-of-the-api-report-postman.pdf" rel="nofollow ugc noopener">Postman 2023 State of API Report</a>:</p>
<img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33f2c858-4163-4ffb-8d6e-77149ac7faa0_458x582.png" alt="Bar chart" width="60%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">
<p></p><p>However, if you’re working with complex data and evolving requirements, GraphQL could be the right tool for the job.</p>
<p/>
<h1 class="header-anchor-post">Consuming GraphQL APIs</h1>
<p>API clients tend to have the same structure:</p>
<ul><li>Schema representation (retrieved using an introspective query),</li>
    <li>A window for entering your query based on the schema, and</li>
    <li>A window displaying the response.</li>
</ul>
<div class="captioned-image-container">
    <img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F38b8eba9-aa18-4d61-8229-e910ac377a20_1063x566.png" alt="Screenshot of Postman Client" style="width:100%">
</div>
<p>The structure of the response depends on the structure of the query, e.g.</p>
<code><pre>query {
  person(personID: &quot;14&quot;) {
    name
    starshipConnection {
      starships {
        name
      }
    }
  }
}</pre></code>

<p>Returns this: </p>
<code><pre>{
  &quot;data&quot;: {
    &quot;person&quot;: {
      &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Han Solo&quot;,
      &quot;starshipConnection&quot;: {
        &quot;starships&quot;: [
          {
            &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Millennium Falcon&quot;
          },
          {
            &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Imperial shuttle&quot;
          }
        ]
      }
    }
  }
}</pre></code>
<p>
(example from the <a href="https://graphql.org/swapi-graphql/" target="_blank">Star Wars GraphQL API</a>.)</p>
<p>Field names can be altered using aliases, so in the above query specifying</p>
<code><pre>fullname: name</pre></code>
<p>returns </p>
<code><pre>&quot;fullname&quot;: &quot;Han Solo&quot;</pre></code>
<p>Directives can be used to add logic based on variables - the following would return the value for <code>model</code> depending on whether <code>fullDetails</code> was true or false thanks to <code>@include</code>:</p>
<code><pre>query ($fullDetails: Boolean!){
  person(personID: &quot;14&quot;) {
    fullname: name
    starshipConnection {
      starships {
        name
        model @include(if: $fullDetails)
      }
    }
  }
} </pre></code>
<p>Queries can be broken into fragments, the same way that applications are broken into components. If <code>starships </code>and<code> vehicles </code>were derived from an overarching <code>Transport </code>type, the fields within both could be requested like this:</p>
<code><pre>query {
  person(personID: &quot;1&quot;) {
    fullname: name
    starshipConnection {
      starships {
        ...vehicleAndStarshipFields
      }
    }
    vehicleConnection{
      vehicles{
        ...vehicleAndStarshipFields
      }
    }
  }
}

fragment vehicleAndStarshipFields on Transport {
  name
  model
}</pre></code>
<p>Which would return in this format:</p>
<code><pre>{
  &quot;data&quot;: {
    &quot;person&quot;: {
      &quot;fullname&quot;: &quot;Luke Skywalker&quot;,
      &quot;starshipConnection&quot;: {
        &quot;starships&quot;: [
          {
            &quot;name&quot;: &quot;X-wing&quot;,
            &quot;model&quot;: &quot;T-65 X-wing&quot;
          },
          {
            &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Imperial shuttle&quot;,
            &quot;model&quot;: &quot;Lambda-class T-4a shuttle&quot;
          }
        ]
      },
      &quot;vehicleConnection&quot;: {
        &quot;vehicles&quot;: [
          {
            &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Snowspeeder&quot;,
            &quot;model&quot;: &quot;t-47 airspeeder&quot;
          },
          {
            &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Imperial Speeder Bike&quot;,
            &quot;model&quot;: &quot;74-Z speeder bike&quot;
          }
        ]
      }
    }
  }
}</pre></code>
<p>If we want to do a union on different object types, we can:</p>
<code><pre>query Search($name: String!) {
  search(name: $name) {
    ... on Person {
      name
      birthYear
    }
    ... on Planet {
      name
      climate
    }
  }
}</pre></code>
<p>This would return different fields, depending on whether the <code>name</code> was for a Person like “Luke Skywalker” or a planet like “Tatooine”.</p>
<p>Enabling each of these scenarios is driven by the structure of the schema.</p>
<h1 class="header-anchor-post">Building GraphQL APIs</h1>
<p></p>
<h2 class="header-anchor-post">Schemas</h2>
<ul>
    <li>Mandatory, which also means every GraphQL API is fully self-documented.</li>
    <li>Contains definitions for:
        <ul>
            <li>Data Structures,</li>
            <li>Queries for retrieving data,</li>
            <li>Mutations for modifying data, and</li>
            <li>Subscriptions, for detecting external changes to data.</li>
        </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
<br/>
<h2 class="header-anchor-post">Resolvers</h2>
<ul>
    <li>Used to ‘resolve’ each field defined in the schema.</li>
    <li>Populates data from a variety of data sources.</li>
    <li>Include four parameters:
        <ul>
            <li>Parent: Result of previous executed resolver. Can also be used as a data source.</li>
            <li>Args: Arguments in the query.</li>
            <li>Context: Shared across all resolvers, contains information such as the users authentication details and database connection details.</li>
            <li>Info: Additional information, useful for debugging.</li>
        </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
<br/>
<h2 class="header-anchor-post">Security</h2>
<ul>
    <li>Includes wide flexibility in options, and depends on your use case.</li>
    <li>Authentication:  Can be done using middleware to intercept the requests before they reach your resolvers. <a href="https://github.com/auth0/express-jwt" target="_blank">Express-jwt</a> is one example of a library for validating JSON Web Tokens.</li>
    <li>Authorisation: Regardless of which logic used, I’d recommend abstracting it away from the resolvers and having them call the logic as needed. <a href="https://the-guild.dev/graphql/shield" target="_blank">GraphQL Shield</a> is an example of one common way to implement.</li>
    <li>The flexibility of GraphQL can put the API at risk of a denial-of-service attack through overly complex queries that consume all available resources. Mitigate via:
        <ul>
            <li>Complexity thresholds (through libraries such as <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/graphql-query-complexity" target="_blank">graphql-query-complexity</a>),</li>
            <li>Depth of query limits (using library <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/graphql-depth-limit" target="_blank">graphql-depth-limit</a>),</li>
            <li>Rate limiting, caching, pagination, and any number of other standard approaches to ensure security.</li>
        </ul>
    </li>
</ul>
<br/>
<h2 class="header-anchor-post">Observability</h2>
<p>There are a number of tools available, including Apollo Studio, Prisma, GraphiQL, and New Relic. Each of these is able to track performance and errors as needed.</p>
<br/>
<h2 class="header-anchor-post">…But Can We Use AI With GraphQL?</h2>
<p>Yes!</p>AI APIs can be used as a data source, but for using AI in the creation of queries there is <a href="https://www.gqlpt.dev/" target="_blank">GQLPT</a> -  where you can leverage AI to generate GraphQL queries from plain text.</p>
<h1 class="header-anchor-post">Summary</h1>
<p>GraphQL can be a useful tool, when used in the right scenarios.  Use it when working with complex data and evolving requirements, make sure you consider security as you would with any API, and it can be a powerful complement to your other existing REST APIs.</p>
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following notes are designed to complement my presentation on GraphQL. Link to the talk will be provided when available. Until recently, I only had a vague understanding of what GraphQL was. For those that still aren’t sure, please know that it’s ok not to know. There are so many buzzwords and new technologies being created all the time, it would be impossible to keep up with absolutely everything. In fact, it happens so often that IBM even created a chart to document the process that happens each time - this is the hype cycle of emerging technologies: This chart goes through five phases: The Innovation Trigger, where the technology is made available to the public for the first time, The Peak of Inflated Expectations occurs shortly after, as everyone attempts to apply the technology to resolve every scenario ever, The Trough of Disillusionment is when people realise that the technology did not in fact fix everything, The Slope of Enlightenment happens as people start using the technology again, but this time with more realistic expectations, and The Plateau of Productivity occurs when the technology has found it’s place in the technological landscape and is used in appropriate scenarios. Currently, I think GraphQL is coming out of the Slope of Enlightenment and starting to head into the Plateau of Productivity, which also means it’s worth doing a refresher for those of us that missed it the first time around. Why GraphQL Was Created Back in the distant past of 2012, Facebook was having some issues with its app. At the time it was essentially an adaptation of the website, and compared to other natively built apps it simply wasn’t working as well - so they decided it was time to rewrite it. Originally they intended to use the existing APIs that they had at the time, which like the majority of the industry were mostly REST APIs. REST Strengths Great when working with simple and less volatile data. Has individual endpoints that correspond with its available resources, meaning there’s a nice inbuilt separation of concerns already. Having stateless operations means that each request is self-contained, which improves scalability and simplifies the underlying back-end architecture. Interfaces well with older systems and technologies, which is great when you’re working with legacy systems. REST Weaknesses REST is less effective when working with complex data, such as was required by Facebook to populate the newsfeed. To do so could involve a number of separate REST calls; to get the user’s list of friends, to get the recent statuses made by each of those friends, to get the comments for each of the statuses, to get the likes of the comments of the statuses of the friends… Doing so would result in an over-fetching risk as additional unnecessary data would be retrieved unnecessarily, Yet it also suffered from under-fetching as all the multiple calls would be required each time the newsfeed is loaded. All that additional traffic adds up, and would be especially noticeable on the phones popular back in 2012, which usually only had 1GB RAM. Also, all those endpoints from before? Well, any new requirements result in additional endpoints being created, and all the existing ones have ongoing maintenance, including versioning and deprecation. How GraphQL Resolves This Instead of traditional approaches, GraphQL works by modelling data as a graph, where data types (like users, posts, comments) are nodes, and the relationships between them (like users posting comments) are the edges connecting those nodes. In this structure, you can traverse between related types, much like how you can move across nodes in a graph. Instead of endpoints, with GraphQL it was now possible to use queries (similar to SQL) to specify exactly what data was required for each use case. This nicely solves both the over-fetching and under-fetching issues. This increased data efficiency also means it’s more practical for providing real-time data updates. You didn't even have to keep building out endpoints for scenarios. For anything with evolving requirements, it became easy to add in fields without breaking previous versions of the query endpoint. GraphQL can also return partial data along with error details, which can be useful when diagnosing issues. This does not mean that GraphQL is perfect for every scenario - there’s a reason why REST APIs are still more common, as shown in the Postman 2023 State of API Report: However, if you’re working with complex data and evolving requirements, GraphQL could be the right tool for the job. Consuming GraphQL APIs API clients tend to have the same structure: Schema representation (retrieved using an introspective query), A window for entering your query based on the schema, and A window displaying the response. The structure of the response depends on the structure of the query, e.g. query { person(personID: &quot;14&quot;) { name starshipConnection { starships { name } } } }]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In The Deep End</title><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/08/29/InTheDeepEnd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In The Deep End" /><published>2024-08-29T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-08-29T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/08/29/InTheDeepEnd</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/08/29/InTheDeepEnd.html"><![CDATA[<span>Exposure to a wider range of technology processes and services can be great for your career. Earlier this year, I changed jobs to do just that - moving from working with a specialised area to a more widely used technology. Apart from broadening your range of skills, working in a new environment can also be great for your career in terms of building cross-industry knowledge, providing networking opportunities, and challenging yourself in new capacities.</span><br /></p>
<h3 class="header-anchor-post">Skill Diversification</h3>
No two teams work the same way, but there can be a lot of overlap in the processes. Taking part in a variety of teams, roles, and workplaces will almost inevitably expose you to a myriad of tools and methods. For example, since changing jobs, I've begun working extensively with CI tools like TeamCity and deployment automation tools like Octopus Deploy, as well as diving into API development. These new skills have not only broadened my technical expertise but also opened up opportunities for me to work on more complex and dynamic projects. Diversifying the number of skills you have and tools you have mastered will open up your opportunities to a wider range of options.</span><br /></p>
<h3 class="header-anchor-post">Unique Perspective with Cross-Industry Knowledge</h3>
Working in a range of different areas means that you can take your learnings from previous experiences and apply them to new contexts. The greater diversity of experience you have, the greater diversity of thought you will be able to bring to new projects, enabling some truly innovative and out-of-the-box solutions.</span><br /></p>
<h3 class="header-anchor-post">Networking Opportunities</h3>
This may be stating the obvious, but did you know different people work in other teams? Shocking, I know. Interacting with new teams and their stakeholders will help you broaden your professional network. Connecting with more peers, mentors, and industry leaders is another excellent way to gain exposure to new ideas and opportunities.</span><br /></p>
<h3 class="header-anchor-post">A New Challenge</h3>
Sometimes, we just get bored and need a change. Changing our work is one sure-fire way to mitigate any sensation of boredom, as it's much more difficult to be bored when figuring out a whole new way of working.  This shake-up can be great for our mental health, as increased variety can keep your work feeling engaging and stimulate continuous learning.</span><br /></p><p>Change can be intimidating, but it is essential for personal growth. Working in a new team or with a new technology enables you to diversify your skills, gain cross-industry knowledge, network with more people, and face new challenges - all of which can enhance your professional growth, satisfaction, and opportunities. If you’re feeling stuck, step out of your comfort zone and dive into the deep end. Embrace the new experiences and opportunities, and discover what is waiting for you out there.</p>
<br>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exposure to a wider range of technology processes and services can be great for your career. Earlier this year, I changed jobs to do just that - moving from working with a specialised area to a more widely used technology. Apart from broadening your range of skills, working in a new environment can also be great for your career in terms of building cross-industry knowledge, providing networking opportunities, and challenging yourself in new capacities. Skill Diversification No two teams work the same way, but there can be a lot of overlap in the processes. Taking part in a variety of teams, roles, and workplaces will almost inevitably expose you to a myriad of tools and methods. For example, since changing jobs, I've begun working extensively with CI tools like TeamCity and deployment automation tools like Octopus Deploy, as well as diving into API development. These new skills have not only broadened my technical expertise but also opened up opportunities for me to work on more complex and dynamic projects. Diversifying the number of skills you have and tools you have mastered will open up your opportunities to a wider range of options. Unique Perspective with Cross-Industry Knowledge Working in a range of different areas means that you can take your learnings from previous experiences and apply them to new contexts. The greater diversity of experience you have, the greater diversity of thought you will be able to bring to new projects, enabling some truly innovative and out-of-the-box solutions. Networking Opportunities This may be stating the obvious, but did you know different people work in other teams? Shocking, I know. Interacting with new teams and their stakeholders will help you broaden your professional network. Connecting with more peers, mentors, and industry leaders is another excellent way to gain exposure to new ideas and opportunities. A New Challenge Sometimes, we just get bored and need a change. Changing our work is one sure-fire way to mitigate any sensation of boredom, as it's much more difficult to be bored when figuring out a whole new way of working. This shake-up can be great for our mental health, as increased variety can keep your work feeling engaging and stimulate continuous learning.Change can be intimidating, but it is essential for personal growth. Working in a new team or with a new technology enables you to diversify your skills, gain cross-industry knowledge, network with more people, and face new challenges - all of which can enhance your professional growth, satisfaction, and opportunities. If you’re feeling stuck, step out of your comfort zone and dive into the deep end. Embrace the new experiences and opportunities, and discover what is waiting for you out there.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pride in June</title><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/06/25/PrideInJune.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pride in June" /><published>2024-06-25T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-06-25T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/06/25/PrideInJune</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/06/25/PrideInJune.html"><![CDATA[<p><span>It’s pride month! The time of year dedicated to celebrating the successes and raising awareness for the challenges still faced by the LGBTQ+ community. With the rise of anti-LGBTQ+ legislation sweeping the US in recent years and the seeming </span><a href="https://apnews.com/article/pride-target-lgbtq-0d0ade0c3ba9766884a9ed7ad92f31fe" target="_blank">lack of brands showing solidarity</a><span> this time around, it seemed an appropriate time to look back on the history and significance of the event.</span></p><p>While LGBTQ+ people have been around for as long as people have in general, this particular month of celebration has its roots in the 1960s. If you, like myself, were not around for this decade - consider the following:</p>
<ul>
    <li>
        <p><span>Homosexuality was considered a mental disorder in the </span><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diagnostic_and_Statistical_Manual_of_Mental_Disorders" target="_blank">Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</a></em><span> (and was not completely removed until 1987).</span></p></li>
    <li>
        <p><span>People were also losing their jobs. For example in 1953 American </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/President_of_the_United_States" target="_blank">President</a><span> </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dwight_D._Eisenhower" target="_blank">Dwight D. Eisenhower</a><span> issued </span><strong>Executive Order 10450,</strong><span> in which federal agencies were charged with reviewing their employees for anyone considered a security risk - which included anyone deemed to have a ‘sexual perversion’. They were seen as more susceptible to blackmail and were fired accordingly.</span></p>
    </li>
</ul>
<p>
There had been numerous movements, organisations, and protests prior, but it was the Stonewall Inn raid that sparked the gay liberation movement in the Western world. Taking place over multiple nights starting on June 28, 1969, police raided the Stonewall Inn in Manhattan. There, officers attempted to arrest any patrons dressed in a way that did not conform to the conventions of their perceived gender.</p><p>This was not an irregular event for gay bars in the city at the time. What was different this time, however, was that as the raid progressed a crowd began to form (consisting of patrons that had been released as well as passers-by). As they watched fights break out between police and those they had arrested, the crowd also grew violent as they transformed into a mob in their attempt to stop the injustice.</p>
<p>
There are plenty of articles and books that will do greater justice to explaining the events and impact of these riots than I am currently capable of doing. David Carter, author of Stonewall: The Riots that Sparked the Gay Revolution, wrote:</p><blockquote><p><em>‘Compared to these earlier events, Stonewall was of a different order for four reasons: it was the only sustained uprising, lasting six days; it was the only one that involved thousands of people; it was the only one that got much media coverage; and it was unique in engendering a new kind of militant organization (first the Gay Liberation Front and later the Gay Activists Alliance) as well as a new political ideology known as ”gay liberation.”’ - </em><a href="https://glreview.org/article/article-509/" target="_blank">What Made Stonewall Different</a></p></blockquote>
<p>
One year later, on the first anniversary of the Stonewall riots, the first Gay Pride marches in US history took place.</p><p>Over time, it extended from a day to a month-long event thanks to the collective efforts of various parts of the LGBTQ+ community. As far as I can tell, there was no particular single originator of the idea to extend the day to a month. Regardless, making the event longer enables a variety of events to take place. From parades to educational sessions, art exhibits, etc, a greater spotlight can shine on the progress made so far, sparking a wider conversation about the issues ongoing.</p>
<p>
<span>Unfortunately, while much has progressed since the original riots, there are still many inequalities that need addressing. With events organised globally (and available as virtual as well as in person), I recommend finding out about the Pride events happening near you, and how you can take part. Just remember, recognition and celebration of rights should not only be contained to a single month. There are still plenty of ways to </span><a href="https://hbr.org/2023/04/research-how-to-be-a-better-ally-to-the-lgbtq-community" target="_blank">support the community</a><span> and fight for equality, regardless of the time of year.</span></p>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s pride month! The time of year dedicated to celebrating the successes and raising awareness for the challenges still faced by the LGBTQ+ community. With the rise of anti-LGBTQ+ legislation sweeping the US in recent years and the seeming lack of brands showing solidarity this time around, it seemed an appropriate time to look back on the history and significance of the event.While LGBTQ+ people have been around for as long as people have in general, this particular month of celebration has its roots in the 1960s. If you, like myself, were not around for this decade - consider the following: Homosexuality was considered a mental disorder in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (and was not completely removed until 1987). People were also losing their jobs. For example in 1953 American President Dwight D. Eisenhower issued Executive Order 10450, in which federal agencies were charged with reviewing their employees for anyone considered a security risk - which included anyone deemed to have a ‘sexual perversion’. They were seen as more susceptible to blackmail and were fired accordingly. There had been numerous movements, organisations, and protests prior, but it was the Stonewall Inn raid that sparked the gay liberation movement in the Western world. Taking place over multiple nights starting on June 28, 1969, police raided the Stonewall Inn in Manhattan. There, officers attempted to arrest any patrons dressed in a way that did not conform to the conventions of their perceived gender.This was not an irregular event for gay bars in the city at the time. What was different this time, however, was that as the raid progressed a crowd began to form (consisting of patrons that had been released as well as passers-by). As they watched fights break out between police and those they had arrested, the crowd also grew violent as they transformed into a mob in their attempt to stop the injustice. There are plenty of articles and books that will do greater justice to explaining the events and impact of these riots than I am currently capable of doing. David Carter, author of Stonewall: The Riots that Sparked the Gay Revolution, wrote:‘Compared to these earlier events, Stonewall was of a different order for four reasons: it was the only sustained uprising, lasting six days; it was the only one that involved thousands of people; it was the only one that got much media coverage; and it was unique in engendering a new kind of militant organization (first the Gay Liberation Front and later the Gay Activists Alliance) as well as a new political ideology known as ”gay liberation.”’ - What Made Stonewall Different One year later, on the first anniversary of the Stonewall riots, the first Gay Pride marches in US history took place.Over time, it extended from a day to a month-long event thanks to the collective efforts of various parts of the LGBTQ+ community. As far as I can tell, there was no particular single originator of the idea to extend the day to a month. Regardless, making the event longer enables a variety of events to take place. From parades to educational sessions, art exhibits, etc, a greater spotlight can shine on the progress made so far, sparking a wider conversation about the issues ongoing. Unfortunately, while much has progressed since the original riots, there are still many inequalities that need addressing. With events organised globally (and available as virtual as well as in person), I recommend finding out about the Pride events happening near you, and how you can take part. Just remember, recognition and celebration of rights should not only be contained to a single month. There are still plenty of ways to support the community and fight for equality, regardless of the time of year.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Just Five More Minutes: Applying Social Media Consumption Tactics To Books</title><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/04/30/SocialMediaTacticsBooks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Just Five More Minutes: Applying Social Media Consumption Tactics To Books" /><published>2024-04-30T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-04-30T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/04/30/SocialMediaTacticsBooks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/04/30/SocialMediaTacticsBooks.html"><![CDATA[I don’t like social media. Sure it has its uses, in enabling me to keep in contact with family and friends across the world, and sure it’s occasionally filled with photos of kittens and puppies and whatnot, but I still don’t like it. I don’t like the fact that I can doom-scroll for hours, or that I do so on far too regular a basis. I don’t think anyone does, and so this presumably isn’t shocking news.
<p/>
What I do like though, is reading. Not memes and status updates, but stories. Yet no matter how much I enjoy it, I never seem to find the time to read, but I always have too much time for social media.
<p/>
I know that social media companies have put a lot of effort and research into making their apps as addictive as possible, to hold user engagement. I also know that I am susceptible to the tactics they have used, as evidenced by my sheer amount of social media usage.
<p/>
So why not try apply the same tactics that have worked so well on me, to reading? Can I make reading books as addictive as social media?
<p/>
There are a few methods that companies use that I focused on to emulate for my experiment. They are; endless scrolling, push notifications, and social comparison.

<p/>

<h2 class="section-heading">Endless Scrolling</h2>
<br/>
<img src="http://blogs.studentlife.utoronto.ca/lifeatuoft/files/2015/11/thisissomuchfun.gif" alt="Image of hand scrolling the text 'This is so much fun' on a phone" width="60%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">
<p/>
As the name suggests, endless scrolling is an interaction design pattern, where content loads as the person scrolls without interruption. Most ebook apps use pagination, where the person flips the pages just like they would with a physical book. Flipping to the next page uses more effort than scrolling down slightly, and it also gives you a natural point in the process to decide to stop reading and do something else. By switching to an infinite scroll model, it requires much less energy to view the next part of content, and as there’s no ‘checkpoint’ where you stop momentarily, you are much more likely to continue passively consuming the content.
<p/>
To enable this for my reading, I switched from the app I was using to use Kindle, which has inbuilt settings to allow for the endless scroll.

<p/>

<h2 class="section-heading">Push Notifications</h2>
<br/>
<img src="https://cdn.dribbble.com/users/409677/screenshots/3947273/noti-ps.gif" alt="A phone with a notification speech bubble floating above it" width="60%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">
<br/>

Spend any time near a modern phone, and you’ll know everything you need about push notifications. Multiple studies have demonstrated the effectiveness of push notifications in regards to user engagement and retention. According to the <a href="https://www.humanetech.com/brain-science" target="_blank">Center for Humane Technology</a>, “Notifications (vibrations, red dots, flashing lights, banners) constantly trigger the salience network, effectively fooling us that something new but trivial is urgent.” If you want to make notifications even more effective, they should also include an element of novelty. Novelty in activity results in several impacts on the brain, and the most valuable impact in this context is that it can induce a release of dopamine, aka the “feel-good” hormone.
<p/>
To replicate this for reading, I used a reminder app (<a href="https://keep.google.com/" target="_blank">Google Keep</a>) to send me a variety of different notifications at varying times.
<p/>
<img src="/img/posts/BookNotifications.jpg" alt="Screenshot of notifications, including 'The world can wait, but your book can't', 'Pause, breathe, and read', 'It's reading o'clock', 'Time to book some reading time!', 
Bookmark now for reading!', 'A book a day keeps reality away', 'Time to read!', and 'Reading? How novel'" style="width:60%;display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">

<p/>

<h2 class="section-heading">Social Comparison</h2>
<br/>
<img src="https://cdn.dribbble.com/users/1129235/screenshots/3362278/gif5.gif" alt="Three people stood on rising and lowering platforms. The person in the centre is sad when their platform is lower than the others." width="60%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">
<br/>

Humans are social animals. We thrive because of connection and cooperation. We also thrive by comparison, as we evaluate our traits and abilities by contrasting ourselves with our peers. Social media allows us to overload on a distorted and over-sanitized version of this, as we can use it to compare ourselves with the very best achievements of every person we have ever met (resulting in <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10309264/" target="_blank">impacted levels of self-esteem</a>, to the surprise of no one).
<p/>
To apply social comparison to reading, all you need is to sign up to a website such as Goodreads or StoryGraph. In both sites, users can record which books they have read before, are reading currently, what they thought of them, what they want to read next, and how many books they have read this year so far. More importantly, you can then connect with others and see what they read, what they rate, and compare just how much more they have read than you so far this year.

<p/>

<h2 class="section-heading">The Results</h2>
<p/>
Before I started this experiment, I was about halfway through reading Great Expectations by Charles Dickens, and it had taken me 12 weeks to reach that point. After I implemented the changes described above, I finished reading the second half of the book in 10 days. I would marvel at how much of an impact it made, but right now I’d rather get back to reading.
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I don’t like social media. Sure it has its uses, in enabling me to keep in contact with family and friends across the world, and sure it’s occasionally filled with photos of kittens and puppies and whatnot, but I still don’t like it. I don’t like the fact that I can doom-scroll for hours, or that I do so on far too regular a basis. I don’t think anyone does, and so this presumably isn’t shocking news. What I do like though, is reading. Not memes and status updates, but stories. Yet no matter how much I enjoy it, I never seem to find the time to read, but I always have too much time for social media. I know that social media companies have put a lot of effort and research into making their apps as addictive as possible, to hold user engagement. I also know that I am susceptible to the tactics they have used, as evidenced by my sheer amount of social media usage. So why not try apply the same tactics that have worked so well on me, to reading? Can I make reading books as addictive as social media? There are a few methods that companies use that I focused on to emulate for my experiment. They are; endless scrolling, push notifications, and social comparison.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Get To The Point</title><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/03/12/GetToThePoint.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Get To The Point" /><published>2024-03-12T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-03-12T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/03/12/GetToThePoint</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/03/12/GetToThePoint.html"><![CDATA[How many words do you need?
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How many words do you need?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review: Your Head Is A Houseboat by Campbell Walker</title><link href="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/01/12/Book-Head-Houseboat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review: Your Head Is A Houseboat by Campbell Walker" /><published>2024-01-12T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-01-12T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/01/12/Book-Head-Houseboat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://rebeccaplatt.com/2024/01/12/Book-Head-Houseboat.html"><![CDATA[It’s that time of year again, when people start taking stock of the year that was and think ahead wondering how they can improve their lives. Countless New Year's resolutions are being planned at this very moment. For a fair few people, their resolutions will involve focusing on improving their mental health. It’s a worthy goal no matter what your mental landscape is like. With that in mind, ‘Your Head Is A Houseboat: A Chaotic Guide to Mental Clarity’ by Campbell Walker is a great book, one that anyone on a (mental) self-improvement journey should read.
<p/>
<img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/81yJxESnSFL._SL1500_.jpg" alt="Book Cover for Your Head is a Houseboat: A Chaotic Guide to Mental Clarity By Campbell Walker" width="60%" style="display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">About The Author</h2>
Campbell Walker, also known as Struthless, is a content creator on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@struthless" target="_blank">YouTube</a> (and various other platforms) that I’ve been following for a few years now.
<p/>
He makes great videos about so many interesting topics, with the overall theme of the videos covering self-reflective journaling, art, and introspection. In general (and based entirely on the content he produces), he seems like a decent guy who’s just trying to make everyone’s head a nicer place to live in.
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">What The Book Is About</h2>
Achieving mental clarity by taking complex concepts and the latest advances in psychology, and making them more accessible to the average person through a fully illustrated houseboat tour metaphor. To the surprise of absolutely no one familiar with Cam’s content, the book is filled with anthropomorphic metacognitions in the form of mean bosses and sock puppets and animals, as well as journaling exercises at the end of each chapter to ensure that the reader fully understands the concepts presented before moving on to the next section.
<p/>
<h2 class="section-heading">My Thoughts</h2>
I have to hand it to him, ‘mental clarity’ was a great description of exactly what this book provides. Several times when I was following along with the activities at the end of the chapters I’d have an epiphany, followed by moments of genuine relief from the constant never ending thought process that is my brain. I actually felt moments of clarity. While I enjoy his videos, I truly did not expect to be as impacted by the book as I was. The concepts covered in the book were not new to me, but the way in which they were covered brought everything into a new light. The analogies resonated with me, and the full-colour illustrations were such a lovely bonus too. I think that this would be a great book to read regardless of whether it’s your first or fifty-first time reading about mental health and self-development.
<p/>]]></content><author><name>Rebecca Platt</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s that time of year again, when people start taking stock of the year that was and think ahead wondering how they can improve their lives. Countless New Year's resolutions are being planned at this very moment. For a fair few people, their resolutions will involve focusing on improving their mental health. It’s a worthy goal no matter what your mental landscape is like. With that in mind, ‘Your Head Is A Houseboat: A Chaotic Guide to Mental Clarity’ by Campbell Walker is a great book, one that anyone on a (mental) self-improvement journey should read. About The Author Campbell Walker, also known as Struthless, is a content creator on YouTube (and various other platforms) that I’ve been following for a few years now. He makes great videos about so many interesting topics, with the overall theme of the videos covering self-reflective journaling, art, and introspection. In general (and based entirely on the content he produces), he seems like a decent guy who’s just trying to make everyone’s head a nicer place to live in. What The Book Is About Achieving mental clarity by taking complex concepts and the latest advances in psychology, and making them more accessible to the average person through a fully illustrated houseboat tour metaphor. To the surprise of absolutely no one familiar with Cam’s content, the book is filled with anthropomorphic metacognitions in the form of mean bosses and sock puppets and animals, as well as journaling exercises at the end of each chapter to ensure that the reader fully understands the concepts presented before moving on to the next section. My Thoughts I have to hand it to him, ‘mental clarity’ was a great description of exactly what this book provides. Several times when I was following along with the activities at the end of the chapters I’d have an epiphany, followed by moments of genuine relief from the constant never ending thought process that is my brain. I actually felt moments of clarity. While I enjoy his videos, I truly did not expect to be as impacted by the book as I was. The concepts covered in the book were not new to me, but the way in which they were covered brought everything into a new light. The analogies resonated with me, and the full-colour illustrations were such a lovely bonus too. I think that this would be a great book to read regardless of whether it’s your first or fifty-first time reading about mental health and self-development.]]></summary></entry></feed>